<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A rare paterne of iustice and mercy; exemplified in the many notable, and charitable legacies of Sr. Iames Cambel, Knight, and alderman of London, deceased : worthy imitation. Whereunto is annexed A meteor, and A starre : or, Briefe and pleasant meditations of Gods providence to his chosen, of the education of children and of the vertue of love; with other poems. / By Edw: Browne.</title>
            <author>Browne, Edward.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1642</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 166 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 92 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A77664</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing B5105</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E1109_1</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R208421</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99867376</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99867376</idno>
            <idno type="VID">119685</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A77664)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 119685)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 163:E1109[1])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A rare paterne of iustice and mercy; exemplified in the many notable, and charitable legacies of Sr. Iames Cambel, Knight, and alderman of London, deceased : worthy imitation. Whereunto is annexed A meteor, and A starre : or, Briefe and pleasant meditations of Gods providence to his chosen, of the education of children and of the vertue of love; with other poems. / By Edw: Browne.</title>
                  <author>Browne, Edward.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[10], 79, [17], 52 [i.e. 42], [4], 26 p. : ill.  </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>for William Ley at Pauls Chaine, neere Doctors Common,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Printed at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>M DC XLII. [1642]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Engraved portrait of Cambell on frontispiece.</note>
                  <note>P. 42 misnumbered 52.</note>
                  <note>"A meteor" and "A starre" have separate title pages and pagination; register is continuous.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Cambell, James, --  Sir, 1570-1642 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Funeral sermons --  17th century.</term>
               <term>God --  Love --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Providence and government of God --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-01</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-05</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-05</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <group>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:119685:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <p>A rare PATERNE OF Iuſtice <hi>and</hi> Mercy; <hi>Exemplified in</hi> The many notable, and charitable Legacies of S<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Iames Cambel,</hi> Knight, and Alderman of <hi>London,</hi> deceaſed: Worthy imitation. <hi>Whereunto is annexed</hi> A Meteor, and a Starre: OR, Briefe and pleaſant Meditations of Gods Providence to his Choſen, of the Education of Children, and of the vertue of Love; with other Poems. By <hi>Edw: Browne.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <q>
                     <bibl>Pſal. 19. 1.</bibl> 
                     <hi>The heavens declare the glory of God, and the firmament ſheweth his handiworke.</hi>
                  </q>
                  <p>Printed at London for <hi>William Ley</hi> at <hi>Pauls</hi> Chaine, neere Doctors Commons. M DC XLII.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="frontispiece">
                  <pb facs="tcp:119685:2"/>
                  <p>
                     <figure>
                        <figDesc>engraved portrait of James Campbell, wearing the robes and chain of the Lord Mayor of London, by George Glover</figDesc>
                        <head>The Effigies of the right wor<hi rend="sup">ſſ</hi> S<hi rend="sup">r</hi> James Cambell Knight ſometime Lo: Mayor, and Senior Aldrn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of London etc.</head>
                     </figure>
                  </p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:119685:2"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </div>
               <div type="dedication">
                  <pb facs="tcp:119685:3"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:119685:3"/>
                  <head>To the Right Worſhipfull his vertuous and religious Lady, Dame <hi>Rachel Cambel,</hi> Relict Executrix of the laſt Will and Teſtament of Sir <hi>Iames Cambel,</hi> Knight, and Alderman of <hi>London,</hi> deceaſed.</head>
                  <head type="sub">And to the Right Worſhipfull his honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red friends, Sir <hi>Thomas Abdy,</hi> Knight and Baronet, and Mr. <hi>Iames Cambel</hi> Eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire, joint Executors with the ſaid Lady: Grace and peace be multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied.</head>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>Right VVorſhipfull:</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">D</seg>Etraction, <hi>that ugly deformed Hell-borne Monſter, hath of late caſt her poiſoning envi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous breath upon my beſt actions, even upon theſe harmleſſe papers, and would faine beget in you an evill opinion of me, and of my honeſt endeavours,
<pb facs="tcp:119685:4"/> thereby to worke my utter ruine. But I hope the Lord, who knoweth the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tegrity of my heart, and the cleanneſſe of my hands, from doing wrong to any, eſpecially to my late Iudicious loving-Maſter; will worke in you ſuch an heroicall and magnanimous ſpirit, that you will not be infected with ſuch pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtiferous venome, your Worſhips knowing very well, that ſuch</hi> De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tractors <hi>like ravenous Vultures, eate and gnaw upon the very life and live<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lihood of others; onely for their owne ends,</hi> viz. <hi>that they may grow fat and rich thereby, for they care not how they impaire the good name, fame, or reputation of others, ſo they themſelves may get honour and eſteeme, though there be little worth in them, deſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving the ſame. Therefore for vindi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation
<pb facs="tcp:119685:4"/> of my credit in this particular (which now lyes a bleeding) I am in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forced to publiſh that, I intended to keepe private; to ſhew to your Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhips and all other my friends, that I have beene ſo far from intending the leaſt diſgrace, that as I am in duty bound, ſo I have ever ſought the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of my judicious loving Maſter: And I am confident if in theſe workes of mine he had found any thing to his diſparagement, hee would in his life time have ſhowne me my errors, (up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on my requeſt) which he never did, as your Ladiſhip very well knowes. And as it is very well knowne throughout this Citie, that my Maſter in his life did much good to others, eſpecially in Iuſticiarie affaires; ſo, I doe humbly acknowledge, that he did alwayes de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light
<pb facs="tcp:119685:5"/> to doe me good, even to the day of his death. And therefore I thinke it part of my dutie, now hee is departed this tranſitorie life, to expreſſe my thankfull heart for the ſame; which I can no better way perform being I have alread<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>e been<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> ſo preſumptuous as to caſt my unlearned workes into the Preſſe) then to publiſh without flat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terie his many worthie and imparal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leled workes to his never-dying me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morie: That they may bee a meanes to excite and ſtir up others of his qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie to doe workes of charitie to the poore, and judicious benevolence to the rich. Yet I doe ingenuouſly confeſſe, that they deſerve to bee ingraven in Pillars of durable Marble by ſome learned and eloquent</hi> Cicero, <hi>rather then by my ruſtick quill on theſe time<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periſhing
<pb facs="tcp:119685:5"/> papers. For my workes, I commit them to your gracious accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, and judicious cenſure, hoping that what I have done amiſſe herein, you will be pleaſed favourably to paſſe by, becauſe you know the attractive cauſe from whence theſe cloudie and muddie vapours did ariſe; therefore I doubt not but the</hi> ſun-ſhine <hi>of your</hi> favourable <hi>aſpects will expell ſuch miſtie</hi> exhalations, <hi>and ever remain upon the poore and weake, yet honeſt and willing endeavours of</hi>
                  </p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>Your unworthy, yet truly faithfull ſervant, Edward Browne.</signed>
                     <dateline>
                        <date>19. Maii. 1642.</date>
                     </dateline>
                  </closer>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div type="text">
                  <pb facs="tcp:119685:6"/>
                  <pb n="1" facs="tcp:119685:6"/>
                  <head>A RARE PATERNE of Iuſtice and Mercy. <hi>Exemplified in the many judicious, noble, and charitable Legacies given and bequeathed in the laſt Will and teſtament of that grave Iudicous Sena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor Sir</hi> James Cambel, <hi>Knight, ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time Lord Maior and ſenior Alderman of London, who departed this tranſitory life upon Wedneſday the fift day of Ia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuary,</hi> Anno Dom. 1641. <hi>and was buried in the Pariſh Church of Saint</hi> Olaves <hi>Iewry, London the 8. day of February following being Tueſday.</hi> Obiit ſine prole, Aetatis ſuae 72.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>THe memory of the juſt is bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed,</hi> ſaith the Wiſeman, <hi>but the name of the the wicked
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:119685:7"/> ſhall rot. And ſurely the righteous ſhall bee had in everlaſting remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance,</hi> ſaith holy DAVID. Yet the Prophet ESAY com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaines, <hi>That the righteous periſh, and no man conſidereth it in heart: and mercifull men are taken away, and no man underſtandeth, That the righteous are taken away from the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill to come.</hi> In conſideration whereof, that I may not be cul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable of the like reproofe, I will with the Pſalmiſt, <hi>marke the up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right man, and behold the juſt, for the end of that man is peace.</hi> For there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by I ſhall learn how to dye com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortably. It may bee as a paterne or example to direct me and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers in the houre of death. For eth wicked they dye either ſot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſhly,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:119685:7"/> impatiently, or deſperately.</p>
                  <p>Firſt, ſottiſhly like blocks and idiots, having neither penitent feeling of their ſins, nor comfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table aſſurance of ſalvation. Being like to <hi>Nabal, whoſe heart ten daies before his death, died within him, and he was like a ſtone.</hi> Such men die like lambes, and yet ſhall bee a prey for the devouring Lion; they go quietly like fools to the ſtocks for correction.</p>
                  <p>Secondly, others die impati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently, who do not willingly bear the Lords correction deſerved by their ſins; but rage, fret, and mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mure, as if God dealt too rigo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rouſly with them, and through impatiency will uſe unlawfull meanes for their recovery: as <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haziah</hi>
                     <pb n="4" facs="tcp:119685:8"/> did, who being <hi>ſicke, ſent meſſengers to enquire of Baal zebub the god of Ekren, if he ſhould recover of his diſeaſe.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Thirdly, others die deſperate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, their conſciences accuſing them moſt terribly for their ſins, without any hope of pardon; as <hi>Cain,</hi> who ſaid, <hi>my ſinne is greater then can be forgiven;</hi> or <hi>Iudas,</hi> who deſpairing of pardon for his ſin, in betraying our Saviour, <hi>went and hanged himſelfe.</hi> The conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences of many wicked men lye quietly, and never trouble them all their life time, but are ſtirred up at their death, and then rage and torment them like a mad dogge which is lately awaked out of ſleepe. But the righteous
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:119685:8"/> die moſt comfortably, they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeving in Chriſt, and having re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pented of their ſinnes, are aſſured in their owne ſoules that all their ſinnes are pardoned in Chriſt: they wil make confeſſion of their faith, and give teſtimony of their repentance unto others, for their comfort and example. They will patiently endure all the paines of their ſickneſſe, as <hi>Iob</hi> did, know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that all comes from the Lord, and that it is his fatherly correcti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and a ſigne of his love, <hi>becauſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>e chaſteneth whom he loveth:</hi> yea, they receive their ſickneſſe as the Lords meſſenger, ſpeaking to their ſoules, as the Prophet <hi>Iſaiah</hi> did to <hi>Hezekiah, Put thine houſe in order, for thou ſhalt die and not live;</hi>
                     <pb n="6" facs="tcp:119685:9"/> and therefore they prepare them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves for another world. Ye<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> further, in their ſickneſſe they can pray moſt fervently, as King <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zekiah</hi> did, <hi>Iſaiah</hi> 38. and then they will give moſt fruitfull and comfortable inſtructions to thoſe which they leave behinde. As the Swan ſings moſt ſweetly a little before his death; ſo the righteous ſpeake moſt divinely a little be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore their end. Whoſoever ſear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheth the Scriptures, may read the divine prophecy of <hi>Iacob</hi> unto the twelve Patriarches, <hi>Geneſ.</hi> 49. the holy bleſſing of <hi>Moſes</hi> upon the twelve tribes, <hi>Deut</hi> 33. the godly exhortation of <hi>Ioſua</hi> to the people of Iſrael plac<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>d by h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>m in Cana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an, <hi>Ioſ.</hi> 23. the wiſe counſell of
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:119685:9"/> 
                     <hi>David</hi> unto <hi>Salomon,</hi> who was to ſucceed him in the kingdome: 1 <hi>King.</hi> 2. Whoſoever readeth the Eccleſiaſticall hiſtories, may not onely ſee the vertuous lives, but alſo the Chriſtian like ends of the Saints and Martyrs in the Church. And whoſoever will be preſent at the death of thoſe which truly feare God, may there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by learne how they themſelves ought to die: for when the out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward man doth decay, the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward man is renewed more and more. They ſhew, that the neer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er they doe approach unto their end, the neerer they draw toward heaven.</p>
                  <p>But in theſe our dayes many may be found, who either do not
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:119685:10"/> at all conſider the death of the righteous, or elſe doe conſider it amiſſe. Though it bee a matter worth conſideration; yet ſome doe not conſider it at all: becauſe they ſee ſo many dye, they make the leſſe reckoning of it: till death knocke at their owne doores, they never regard it: they muſt needs dye themſelves, before they can bee brought to conſider of death: they care not who ſinke, ſo they ſwimme; nor how many die, ſo they may live: yea this is greatly to be lamented, that ſome doe regard the death of a Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an, no more then they regard the death of a dog. But ſeeing wee may learne ſo many profitable inſtructions by their death, let us
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:119685:10"/> now begin to conſider it better then ever we did before.</p>
                  <p>Others doe conſider it, but yet amiſſe; either fondly, or froward<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly. Fondly, through naturall af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection ariſing from kindred, affi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie, or familiaritie. If a ſtranger die, it nothing moves them: but if one of their owne friends dye, they ſigh and ſob, they howle and lament. If the father loſe his ſon, he cries moſt pittifully, as <hi>David</hi> did for <hi>Abſalom, O my ſon Abſalom, my ſonne, my ſonne Abſalom: would God I had died for thee: O Abſalom my ſonne, my ſonne.</hi> If the mother loſe her children, ſhee behaveth her ſelfe like <hi>Rachel weeping for her children, and would not be comforted, becauſe they were not.</hi> If children
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:119685:11"/> loſe their parents, they cry after them as <hi>Eliſha</hi> did after <hi>Elias,</hi> when he was taken up, <hi>my father, my father.</hi> If a ſiſter loſe her bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, ſhe weepeth for him, as <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry</hi> did for <hi>Lazarus.</hi> If the husband loſe his wife, he weepeth for her, as <hi>Abraham</hi> wept for <hi>Sarah:</hi> yea he mourneth like a Turtle Dove which hath loſt his marrow. If the wife loſe her husband, ſhee dealeth like <hi>Naomi,</hi> who would not be called <hi>Naomi,</hi> that is, <hi>beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifull:</hi> but <hi>Mara,</hi> that is, <hi>bitter, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the Lord had given her much bitterneſſe.</hi> If one familiar friend loſe another, hee lamenteth his death, as <hi>David</hi> did the death of <hi>Ionathan: Woe is me for thee, my bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Ionathan: very kinde haſt thou
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:119685:11"/> beene unto me: thy love to mee was wonderfull, paſsing the love of women.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Indeed I cannot deny, but that we ought in a ſpeciall manner to conſider the death of thoſe which are neere and deare unto us: for it may be they are taken from us, becauſe wee were unworthy of them; or becauſe we gloried and truſted over much in them, and were not ſo thankfull for them as we ought. If we had any help by them, we muſt conſider, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther God have not deptived us of them, for the puniſhment of our ſinnes, as the widow of <hi>Sarepta</hi> did at the death of her ſonne, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing unto <hi>Eliah: Art thou come unto me to call my ſinne to remembrance, and to ſlay my ſonne?</hi> Yet this con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:119685:12"/> muſt bee ordered by wiſedome, it muſt not be joyned with exceſſive ſorrow. Neither muſt wee conſider their death alone, but alſo the death of others which dye in the Lord, and to learne to make an holy uſe there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of. For as <hi>Sampſon</hi> found ſweet honey in the carcaſſe of a dead Lion; ſo wee may finde ſome ſweet inſtructions in the dead corps of every righteous man: yea the more righteous that they are which doe die, the more ſhould their death be conſidered, becauſe it may yeeld greater ſtore of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction unto us. And it may bee, that God doth take away thoſe which are neare unto us, becauſe wee doe careleſly regard
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:119685:12"/> the death of thoſe which be farre off.</p>
                  <p>Againe, ſome conſider the death of the righteous very fro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardly and peeviſhly, yea I may ſay malitiouſly and prepoſterouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly. For if any of them bee taken away by a ſudden and extraordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary death, they preſently cenſure them as plagued of God, and condemne their former profeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, thinking that God would not have ſo dealt with them, if hee approved either of them or their profeſſion. But they muſt bee inſtructed in this point by wiſe <hi>Salomon,</hi> who ſaith: <hi>that no man knoweth love or hatred of all that is before him. All things come alike to all: and the ſame condition is to the
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:119685:13"/> juſt and the wicked, to the good and the pure, and to the polluted: to him that ſacrificeth, and to him that ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crificeth not. Eli</hi> was a Prieſt, and a good man; yet brake his necke by falling backward from his ſeat. <hi>Ionathan</hi> was a ſworne bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther unto <hi>David,</hi> a godly and faithfull friend; yet was he ſlaine in battell by the hands of the Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſtims. That Prophet of God which came out of <hi>Iudah</hi> to <hi>Beth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>el,</hi> to ſpeak with <hi>Ieroboam,</hi> and the altars which he had built for ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latry, was no doubt an holy man; yet was hee killed in the way by a Lion? <hi>Ioſiah</hi> was a good King, like unto him there was no King before him, neither after him roſe any like him: yet was
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:119685:13"/> he ſlaine in the valley of <hi>Megiddo,</hi> by <hi>Necho</hi> King of <hi>Egypt. Iobs</hi> children were well brought up by their godly father, and it is ſaid that before <hi>Iob</hi> offered ſacrifice for them, they were ſanctified: yet within a while after, as they were eating and drinking in their el<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt brothers houſe, a violent winde overthrew the houſe, and killed them all.</p>
                  <p>Wee muſt not therefore judge of men by their death, but rather by their life. Though ſometime a good death may follow an evill life: yet an evill death can never follow a good life. <hi>Correct thine evill life, and feare not an evill death: he cannot die ill, that lives well,</hi> ſaith <hi>Auguſtine.</hi> And afterward anſwers
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:119685:14"/> the objections of theſe men, and makes this the foot of his ſong<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
                     <hi>Thou wilt ſay unto me, have not many juſt men periſhed by ſhipwracke? cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly, hee cannot die ill, which live<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> well. Have not many juſt men been<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> ſlain by the enemies ſword? Certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, he cannot die ill, which lived well Have not many juſt men beene kille<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> by theeves? Have not many righteou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> men beene torne in pieces by wild<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> beaſts? Certainly, hee cannot die il<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> which lived well, &amp;c.</hi> But I will ſay unto ſuch as cenſure the righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous for their ſtrange and violen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> death, as Chriſt ſaid of thoſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> eighteene, upon whom the wa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> of <hi>Siloam</hi> fel and ſlew them: <hi>Think yee that theſe were greater ſinners then others? I tell you nay; but except
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:119685:14"/> ye repent, ye all ſhall likewiſe periſh.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>As for ſudden death, it is evill to them which lead an evill life, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it findes them unpr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>pared, it carries them away ſuddenly unto torment: but it is not evill to them which live well; becauſe it findes them prepared: it frees them from much paine which o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers endure through long ſick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and carries them forthwith to the place where they deſire to be. The righteous doe ſo diſpoſe of themſelves in the morning, as if they might die before night; and at night, as if they might die before morning: and therefore whenſoever death comes, it finds them prepared, and is a benefit unto them.</p>
                  <pb n="18" facs="tcp:119685:15"/>
                  <p n="2">2 Againe, if the righteous a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle before death, bee dangerouſly tempted by Satan, and ſhew their infirmitie by uttering ſome ſpee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches which tend to doubting or deſperation (though afterward they get victorie, and triumph o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver the divel) carnall people think there is no peace of conſcience, and therefore no ſalvation to bee had, by that religion: and ſo ſpeake evill of it. Let ſuch conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the eſtate of <hi>Iob</hi> in his miſery, <hi>who curſing the day of his birth, ſaid, that the arrowes of the Almighty did ſticke in him, the venome whereof had drunke up his ſpirit: that the ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors of God did fight againſt him, that the Lord was his enemie: did write bitter things againſt him: and did
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:119685:15"/> ſet him as a butt to ſhoot at.</hi> As alſo the eſtate of <hi>David,</hi> through ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror of conſcience, while he con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cealed his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>inne: <hi>His bones con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumed, he roared all the day long, his moiſture was turned into the drought of ſummer.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Againe, let them know, that the devill doth moſt tempt the beſt. Hee then tempted Chriſt, when hee was <hi>baptized and filled with the holy Ghoſt:</hi> ſo will he moſt tempt Chriſtians, when they have received greateſt gifts of Gods Spirit. As theeves labour to breake downe and rob thoſe houſes onely, where great ſtore of treaſure or wealth is laid up; and as Pyrates deſire to take that ſhip which is beſt loaden with
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:119685:16"/> the deareſt merchandize: ſo the Divell doth moſt ſeeke to make a prey of them, which are endued with the greateſt meaſure of ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall graces. When <hi>the ſtrong man armed keepeth the houſe, the things that he poſſeſſeth are in peace; but when a ſtronger then he, overcommeth him,</hi> then he gathereth greater for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and makes a new aſſault to enter againe. In any commotion whom doe Rebels kill and ſpoil? not thoſe which ſubmit them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves unto them, and joyne with them in their rebellion: but thoſe which are faithfull unto their Prince, and fight for their Prince againſt them, as doth appeare now in the <hi>Rebels of Ireland.</hi> Now the Divell is as a Rebell in the
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:119685:16"/> Lords Kingdome; whom then will he moſt trouble and aſſault? not the wicked which ſubmit themſelves unto him, and joyne with him in rebellion againſt God, but the godly which abide faithfull, &amp; fight under the Lords banners againſt him. Whoſoever would reigne with Chriſt in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, muſt overcome the Divell on earth: for he promiſeth, <hi>To him that overcommeth will I grant to ſit with me in my throne, even as I o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vercame, and ſit with my Father in his Throne.</hi> How can there be a victory, where there is no bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tell? And how can there be any battell, where there is not aſſaul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting and reſiſting? And no mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vell though the Divell doe moſt
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:119685:17"/> aſſault the righteous at their death for he taketh the opportunitie of the time, his <hi>wrath is then great: knowing that hee hath but a ſhort time.</hi> Hee muſt either overcome them at that inſtant, or elſe not at all: yea, he takes the advantage of their preſent weakneſs, and thoſe ſinnes which before he perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded people to be ſmall and light, at the time of death hee maketh great and heavie. Even as a tree or piece of wood, while it ſwims in a river ſeemeth to be light, and one may eaſily draw it; but when it comes to the ſhore, and is laid upon dry ground, can ſcarcely be drawne by ten men: ſo ſinne is made light by the Divell ſo long as men live; that ſo hee may ſtill
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:119685:17"/> encourage them to practiſe it: but when it comes to the ſhore of death, then hee makes it heavie, and begins moſt to trouble their conſciences with it, that if it were poſſible they might by it bee brought to deſperation. In the middeſt of the tentation, when the godly ſeeme moſt to over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come, who lyes as though hee were dead; yet hee hath life in him: and therefore as <hi>Paul</hi> ſaw that life was in <hi>Eutiches,</hi> embra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced him, and delivered him alive, when the people tooke him up for dead: and he will at laſt ſo re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtore them, as that they ſhall live for ever.</p>
                  <p n="3">3 Laſtly, others beholding them which were reputed righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous,
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:119685:18"/> to die very ſtrangely, to rave, to blaſpheme, to utter many idle and impious ſpeeches, to bee unruly, and behave themſelves very fooliſhly, they begin to ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect their profeſſion: but let them know, that theſe things may ariſe from the extremity of their diſeaſe. For in hot Fevers and burning Agues, the choler aſcending into the braine, will hinder the uſe of underſtanding, and ſo cauſe them thus to <hi>misbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>have themſelves rather like mad men then Chriſtians.</hi> And therefore as <hi>Paul</hi> ſaid of himſelfe after regene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, <hi>It is no more I that doe it, but the ſin that dwelleth in me:</hi> ſo may I ſay of them, it is not they which doe it, but the diſeaſe which is
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:119685:18"/> upon them. All ſinnes commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by the righteous in thoſe ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tremities, are but ſinnes of igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, becauſe they want the uſe of reaſon to judge of ſinne: they are alſo ſinnes of infirmitie, ari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing from the frailty of their fleſh: and for them they wil afterward repent, if they recover the uſe of reaſon, and bee able to know them to be ſinnes: or if they doe not, they are freely pardoned in the death of Chriſt, as well as o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſinnes bee. Wherefore I ſay to thoſe which cenſure them un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charitably for that their end, as Chriſt ſaid to the Jewes for their carnall cenſure of him, <hi>Iudge not according to the appearance, but judge righteous judgement: yea, judge not,
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:119685:19"/> that yee bee not judged.</hi> For rather then raſhly judge of others, thoſe which ſurvive the righteous have juſt cauſe to feare ſome preſent evils, and labour by unfained re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance, if it be poſſible, to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent them. Their death is a plaine prognoſtication of ſome evils to come, and ſhould bee as a trum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pet to awaken others out of the ſleepe of ſinne. Many of the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked rejoyce when the godly are taken away from them; they love their roomes better then their company; they hated them and their profeſſion in their life time, becauſe, as they ſay, <hi>they are not for our profit, and they are contrary to our doings; they checke us for offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding againſt the law; it grieves us to
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:119685:19"/> looke upon them; for their lives are not like other men;</hi> and therefore at their death they are glad that they are rid of them; when indeed they have greater cauſe to howle and weepe for the miſeries that ſhall come upon them. The righteous need not to imitate the ungodly practice of <hi>Herod,</hi> who being ready to die, and thinking that his death would be a great joy to many, ſhut up in priſon ſome Noblemen in every town; and required his ſiſter <hi>Salome,</hi> and her husband <hi>Alexa,</hi> that ſo ſoone as he was dead, they ſhould kill thoſe Noblemen, and then all <hi>Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dea</hi> would lament his death. The Lord himſelfe doth often make the death of the righteous to bee
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:119685:20"/> lamented, by ſending of extraor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary judgements immediately after their death. When <hi>Noah</hi> en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred into the Arke, the world is drowned with the floud; when <hi>Lot</hi> departs out of <hi>Sodome,</hi> it is burnt with fire.</p>
                  <p n="2">2 In this reſpect alſo the righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous have no cauſe to feare death, but rather to deſire it; for what is it but an ending of ſome troubles and a preventing of others? They may with <hi>Paul, deſire to be looſed &amp; to be with Chriſt, which is beſt of all.</hi> It is true which <hi>Salomon</hi> ſaith, <hi>That the day of a mans death is better then the day of his birth.</hi> For the day of a godly mans birth is the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of his miſerie; but the day of his death is the end of his miſerie.
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:119685:20"/> Indeed the day of a wicked mans death is the moſt wofull day that ever be<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ell him; for he is not ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken away from the evill to come, but he is taken unto evill, to bee tormented in hell for evermore. And therefore hee feares death as much as a malefactor feareth a Serjeant that commeth to carry him to priſon, where he is like to abide till the day of execution. That is true in them which the Divell ſaid, <hi>Skin for skin, and all that ever a man hath, will he give for his life.</hi> And as the Gibeonites were content rather to be bondmen, &amp; hewers of wood, and drawers of water, then to bee killed by the Iſraelites as other nations were: So they had rather indure any
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:119685:21"/> kinde of miſerie, then to die as others doe, becauſe they feare a worſe eſtate after death, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore muſt bee pulled from the earth with as great violence, as <hi>Ioab</hi> was pulled from the hornes of the altar, unto which he had fled as to a place of refuge. But the godly knowing what an hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pie exchange they make by death, they deſire to die ſo ſoone as it pleaſeth the Lord. Indeed none ought for the ending of preſent calamities, or preventing of fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture miſeries, to ſhorten their owne dayes, as <hi>Saul</hi> did by falling on his owne ſword; nor yet for the preſent enjoying of eternall happineſſe, procure their owne death; as <hi>Cleombrotus</hi> did, who
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:119685:21"/> reading <hi>Plato</hi> his booke of the immortalitie of the ſoule, caſt himſelfe headlong from a wall, that he might change this life for a better. He onely who gave life, muſt take it away: and the Lord may ſay to ſuch, <hi>I will receive no ſoules, which againſt my will have gone out of the body; the Philoſophers which did ſo, were martyrs of fooliſh Philoſophy.</hi> Yet ſeeing that death freeth the righteous from preſent and future miſeries, they may be moſt willing to die, ſo ſoone as the Lord calleth for them; and when death approacheth, may ſay with <hi>Simeon, Lord now letteſt thou thy ſervant depart in peace.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="3">3 Laſtly, in this reſpect we muſt learne not to mourne im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moderately
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:119685:22"/> for the death of the righteous Though wee received great comfort, and enjoyed ſome benefit by them while they were alive; as I did by my late Maſter Sir <hi>Iames Cambel;</hi> yet ſeeing that death is an advantage unto them, we ſhould <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ee content patiently to bear our owne loſſe, in reſpect of their great gaine. If two friends ſhould lie in priſon together, or ſhould dwel together in a ſtrange Countrey, where both of them were hardly uſed, were many wayes injured, endured great want, and ſuſtained much miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie; though they loved one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther dearly, and the one were an he<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>pe and comfort to the other; yet if the one ſhould bee taken
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:119685:22"/> from the other, and brought to his chiefeſt friends, and among them be not onely freed from all ſuch miſeries as before he had en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dured, but alſo bee advanced to great preferment; will the other which is left behinde him, be diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>contented at it? Will he not ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther wiſh himſelfe to bee there with him in the like; then deſire, that either hee had ſtayed with him, or might returne againe? This our life is as a priſon, or ſtrange Country, in which wee indure great miſerie, and may e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very day looke for more: if there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore our deareſt friends bee taken from us, freed from theſe miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, and advanced to great glory with Chriſt and his Saints in the
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:119685:23"/> Kingdome of heaven; wee have no cauſe to wiſh, that either they had ſtayed longer with us, or might returne againe unto us; but rather deſire that wee might quickly goe unto them, to bee glorified in like ſort. Though we may thinke that they died too ſoone for us, yet they died not too ſoone for themſelves: for the ſooner they come to reſt and happineſſe, the better it is for them. Their condition is farre better then ours, for they are freed from miſerie; we are reſerved for further miſerie: they are already arrived at the haven of eternall reſt: and we are ſtill toſſed on the ſea of this world, with trouble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome waves, and dangerous tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peſts:
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:119685:23"/> they have ended their jour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney with leſſer travell, and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king a ſhorter cut: and wee are yet travelling with weariſomnes in our journey. If any one of them could ſpeake after their death, he would ſay unto them which weepe for him, as Chriſt ſaid to the daughters of <hi>Ieruſalem, Weepe not for me, but weepe for your ſelves, and for your children;</hi> becauſe of the dangerous dayes that ſhall enſue: Or as Chriſt ſaid unto his Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, <hi>If ye loved me, ye would verily rejoyce, becauſe I goe unto the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>But if examples doe move any thing at all, I may apply all that hath beene ſpoken to this preſent occaſion. A <hi>righteous</hi> man is <hi>pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhed;</hi>
                     <pb n="36" facs="tcp:119685:24"/> a <hi>mercifull</hi> man is <hi>taken a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way;</hi> for God hath made me ſeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly to conſider, and lay cloſe to my heart the loſſe of my late <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicious loving Maſter, Sir <hi>Iames Cambel.</hi> Therefore for a memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riall of him I have preſumed to ſet forth his unparallel'd Legacies. Which though they be unskilful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly performed, yet God may work ſuch an effect in ſome rich mens hearts, that they may be induced thereby to doe ſuch like actions, to Gods praiſe and glory, poore peoples comfort, and their owne honour here, and happines here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after.</p>
                  <p>And to prove Sir <hi>Iames</hi> both a juſt and merciful minded Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, I ſhall write little of things
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:119685:24"/> done by him in his life time, for <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>hen I ſhould run into an endleſſe Labyrinth, and overwhelm my <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>elfe in an ocean of matter; for all <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>hat knew him cannot otherwiſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>udge, but that he was a rare ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample of Juſtice m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>derated by Mercy<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>And in Juſtice and Mercy I comprehend all other Graces, as Piety and Devotion, Wiſedome and Policy, Temperance and Moderation, Fortitude and Cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage, Frugality and good Huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bandry, Long ſuffering and Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience, all <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>heſe were moſt emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent in Sir <hi>Iames</hi> while he lived.</p>
                  <p>Firſt, for his piety and devoti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, his conſtant early riſing on the Lords day to heare Gods word ſincerely preached, and to
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:119685:25"/> joyne himſelfe in the publiqu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> worſhip of God, with the reſt o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> the Congregation in the houſe of prayer. As alſo his often reading the word of God, and earneſt zealous prayer with his family all the dayes in the weeke, can teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie the ſame, of which I have beene an eye witneſſe theſe 18. yeares and upwards.</p>
                  <p n="2">2 For his Wiſedome and Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licie in publique affaires as well as private, I will prove firſt by the teſtimonie of all the whole Senate of this famous Citie Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don, over which he was ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time ſupreme, and 4. yeares, or thereabouts, ſenior Alderman. Secondly, I will produce the French Merchants of this Citie,
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:119685:25"/> over whom hee hath beene Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernour above 20. yeares. And in that Trade he was brought up from his minority under his fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. Thirdly, I will prove his wiſedome and skill in the choice of cloth and wooll, the chiefe commodity of this kingdome, famous above other nations for that golden fleece, from the teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony of all the Merchants of the Staple by whom hee was choſen Maior or chiefe Governour, which in former times was a place of great honour, though now not ſo much eſteemed.</p>
                  <p>Fourthly, I will prove his wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome and ſage advice from the teſtimony of all the Governours of the Hoſpitall, of Saint <hi>Thomas</hi>
                     <pb n="40" facs="tcp:119685:26"/> in Southwarke, over whom hee was Preſident neere 18. yeares. And laſt of all I will prove his wiſedome in all his Judiciary af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faires, from the teſtimony of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny thouſands in this City, as well as from his owne kindred, my ſelfe and others of his family.</p>
                  <p>Thirdly, for his temperance and moderation, firſt in apparell, it is well knowne that as he was no follower himſelfe, ſo he did not approve that others ſhould be attired in vaine, fooliſh, and fantaſticke apparell. Secondly, in his diet he was very temperate, ſo that as he did abhor drunkennes, and gluttony in others, ſo he was a ſtrict obſerver himſelfe. What, and in what meaſure hee did eate
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:119685:26"/> or drinke, for I never ſaw him overtaken with exceſſe, ſince I came unto him. Thirdly, in his words he was a <hi>Moſes,</hi> a man of ſlow ſpeech, and did not delight in vaine babling. But when hee did ſpeake hee would bee ſure it ſhould be to good purpoſe.</p>
                  <p>Fourthly, for his fortitude and courage, I ſhall onely take notice that what buſineſſe ſoever he un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertooke, either publique or pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate upon good and warrantable foundation, he would be ſure to proſecute, maintaine, and hold, as in all theſe places of Judicature where hee was ſeated, it is well knowne.</p>
                  <p>Fifthly, for his frugality and good husbandry, though in ſome
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:119685:27"/> it may be eſteemed covetouſneſſe and avarice, when they ſhall op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe their neighbour, and grind the face of the poore debter for the maintenance of pride and prodigality in their children and kindred. Yet in Sir <hi>Iames</hi> it was a rare vertue: for he was ſo farre from oppreſſing any with tedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous ſuits in law, that to my know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge during the time that I lived with him, he was very unwilling that any ſhould bee caſt into pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon at his ſuit, and would rather agree upon a ſmall compoſition, then take the rigour of the Law againſt any, though he loſt there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by. For I doe not remember that he cauſed above one or two to be arreſted, though he hath had ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:119685:27"/> bad debters, as his Executors ſhall find.</p>
                  <p>But admit he had been a neere, auſtere, and hard man, as is repu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, yet that ſhould not be any diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paragement to his other rare vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues, but rather a commendation. For we reade that God himſelfe, (whoſe example he followed) in Juſtice will looke for a ſevere account of all his ſervants, though he be reputed by the unthankfull wretch a ſevere and hard man for the ſame, reaping where hee ſowed not, and gathering where hee ſtrowed not. And it is but reaſon that hee ſhould have the glory of his owne graces: for he gives the talents of ſpirituall gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces and temporall bleſſings unto
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:119685:28"/> the children of men, to uſe and profit thereby, and not to bee bound up in a napkin, or thrown under a buſhell. And hee com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands that our light ſhould ſo ſhine before men, that they may ſee our good workes, and glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rifie our Father which is in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven. Therefore ſhall any be repu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted covetous or an oppreſſour, for looking to have his owne goods reſtored according to law, that he m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>y husband them him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, for the glory of God, and good of others, as Sir <hi>Iames</hi> did, of whom I may truly ſay with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out flattery, that if any were, he was a ſteward for heaven, in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king friends of his unrighteous Mammon, in thus caſting his
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:119685:28"/> bread upon thoſe waters, and in being thus mercifull unto the poore, ſurely he is received into everlaſting habitations. He hath found the reward of his labours, and God hath ſhewed mercy un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to his ſoule (through Chriſt) as he hath had mercy on the poore.</p>
                  <p>And laſt of all for his patience and long ſuffering, I ſhall onely write this for any judicious rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der to judge, that notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing all my Satyricall writing, yet he was never moved therewith, but as I thought did affect me the better for expending my ſpare time in ſuch divine meditations, and did ſay that God had put into his heart to doe me good, which he hath done accordingly, for if
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:119685:29"/> he had given mee a large portion of wealth, I ſhould have beene proud and idle, but leaving me ſo ſmall a portion for my long ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice, it hath made me humble and induſtrious to publiſh his chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table Legacies for the good of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, to his eternall memory, though I debaſe my ſelfe thereby. And although he was grievouſly pained with the ſtone in the blad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, of which he dyed, yet for my good he was willing to doe any thing which I thought would procure me profit, and never ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med to bee impatient, as many would have beene, had they felt ſuch paine as he did.</p>
                  <p>What ſhall I ſay more? for in him all graces ſeemed to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>catinated
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:119685:29"/> and linked together, ſo that in him they became a chaine of graces, even grace upon grace, which continually increaſed from his birth to his death, for ought I know, becauſe the end crownes all actions, for as a tree growes, ſo it falls, and as man lives, ſo for the moſt part he dyes, except God worke a miracle, as he did at the houre of death upon the Thiefe upon the Croſſe. And the moſt ſafeſt way to judge of a mans actions while he lived, is to conſider his behaviour at his death: yet let us take heed how we raſhly judge any, as is before ſpecified, and rather judge chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tably of all, then uncharitably of any. But Chriſts words are moſt
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:119685:30"/> certainly true, that a bad tree can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not bring forth good fruit, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther can a good tree bring forth evill fruit, for men doe not ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther grapes of thornes, nor figges of thiſtles, therefore by their fruits you ſhall know them.</p>
                  <p>Now it was not my happines to bee with him at the houre of his death, neither did I continue long in his preſence during the time of his ſickneſſe, becauſe I had given him juſt cauſe of of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence by ſome miſdemeanours. And likewiſe becauſe I was ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible of my great loſſe of him in whom I thought my livelihood did conſiſt, for I did ever doubt that he would not beſtow upon me any great benevolence at his
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:119685:30"/> death, becauſe he was ſo willing <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>o doe mee good in his life. Yet this I can teſtifie, that he as <hi>Heze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kiah,</hi> having ſet his houſe in or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, by compoſing of his Will, did prepare himſelfe for death, ſhall I ſay a month or two? nay I may affirme a yeare or two be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he died: during which time hee ſeldome went abroad, but kept in his houſe, and ſpent his ſpare time in reading the Bible, and other good bookes, and in ſinging of Pſalmes, and eſpecially the 39. <hi>Pſal.</hi> which he did often ſing with very much chearfulnes. And upon Newyeares day laſt, perceiving his houre draw neere, ſealed his Will, and went quietly to bed, as to his grave, from
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:119685:31"/> which place he would not be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moved till the houre of his death, which was upon the Wedneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day following betweene ſix and ſeven of the clocke in the mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning.</p>
                  <p>And one thing I cannot but obſerve, that when any came to viſit him during thoſe foure daies, <hi>viz.</hi> from Saturday to Wedneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day, and demanded how he did, he would anſwer, <hi>Sick, as a priſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner in hope:</hi> which me thinks was a heavenly ſpeech, for hee knew his ſoule was impriſoned in a brittle houſe of clay, out of which he hoped ſhe ſhould ſhortly bee delivered, and carried by the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels of God into a heavenly ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitation, to enjoy everlaſting free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:119685:31"/> which I hope hee hath found.</p>
                  <p>But all this while I have ceaſed to treat of Juſtice and Mercy, which was the chiefe of my in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention: for though they may be comprehended in the other fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>named vertues, yet they are more conſpicuous and apparent in his many judiciary and charitable Legacies bequeathed in his laſt Will &amp; Teſtament, which might I have leave to publiſh in his owne words, and make a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentary thereon according to my fancy, me thinkes I could de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribe Juſtice and Mercy in moſt lively colours. For firſt, unto his Lady Juſtice and Mercy met to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether. Juſtice in performance of
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:119685:32"/> his agreement, mercy in remem<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>brance of his love. But in this could have wiſhed that mercy had exceeded juſtice, for as ſhe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> hath beene a loving wife to him neere 24. yeares, ſo it is wel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> knowne that ſhe is a charitabl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> woman; and for that cauſe Si<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>Iames</hi> made her the executrix o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> his Will, which otherwiſe he<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> would not have done. <hi>For I am confident</hi> (ſaith he in one clauſe o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> his Teſtament) <hi>that ſhe will ſee thi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> my Will really performed.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Secondly, Juſtice appeares in his other bequeſts to his kindred and alliance. In that hee hath gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven moſt to them he did leaſt for in his life, ſo that there might be an equivolence amongſt all, and
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:119685:32"/> none to take exception againſt the other.</p>
                  <p>Thirdly, Juſtice appeares in his other bequeſts, eſpecially to his poore ſervants and retainers, that he hath forgot none, but re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membred all in a lumpe of 300. pound, to bee diſpoſed at ſuch times, in ſuch parcels, and to ſuch perſons as his Lady pleaſeth, <hi>ſome of them being ſuch as deſerved no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing,</hi> are his owne words in one clauſe of his will, where they are thus mentioned. And herein was a point of policy, to keepe them under ſubjection, in depending upon her favour. After them hee remembers me with 20. pound, on purpoſe to make me, as I ever thought my ſelfe to be in ſome
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:119685:33"/> ſort like <hi>Iacob,</hi> to depend upon Gods providence on my owne endeavours, that I ſhould ſtrive againſt ſuch oppoſition that ſhould be made againſt me in be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing an actor in the execution of theſe famous Legacies, and if I ſhall deſerve nothing for my paines therein, (according to Sir <hi>Iames</hi> his will) I will have no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing. But letting juſtice and mercy remaine with him in the actions of his life, behold mercy ſhall flouriſh after his death. And as ſhe is over all Gods workes, ſo ſhe hath preheminence over all Sir <hi>Iames</hi> his bequeſts, in a more eminent manner. For hee hath not onely given <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>eliefe to the poore and needy for the preſent,
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:119685:33"/> but for the future. So that theſe 7. workes of Mercy appertaining to the body, according to this verſe,
<q>Viſito, poto, cibo, redimo, tego, colligo, condo,</q> are accompliſhed by Sir <hi>Iames</hi> in his charitable Legacies, for there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in if you doe obſerve, he hath vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſited the ſicke, given drinke to the thirſty, fed the hungry, redeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed captives and priſoners, clothed the naked, lodged the harbour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe, and buried the dead: nay more, hee hath not onely provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded reliefe for the body, but hee hath had regard to the ſoule, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to this ve<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſe:</p>
                  <q>Co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſul<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>, caſtiga, ſolare, remitte, fer, ora.</q>
                  <p>He hath inſtructed the ignorant, corrected the ſinner, comforted
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:119685:34"/> the heavie hearted, forgiven of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fences, borne with the weake, and prayed for all. Therefore there is no queſtion to be made, but that he hath received his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward in part, with an <hi>Euge bone ſerve,</hi> well done good and faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full ſervant, come and receive the kingdome prepared for you from the beginning of the world: for I was hungry, &amp;c.</p>
                  <p>Firſt, that poor children ſhould be wel educated, and brought up in good learning, hee hath given one thouſand Markes for the ere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction and maintenance of a Free-Schoole in the towne of Barking in Eſſex.</p>
                  <p>Secondly, to keep youth from beggery and theevery, which is
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:119685:34"/> begot by ſloath and idleneſſe, the root of all evill, hee hath bequea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thed two thouſand pounds for a ſtocke to keep ſuch at labour and worke in Bridewell, that they as others ſhould labour with their owne hands, and in the ſweat of their browes eate their bread, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording as God commanded <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dams</hi> poſterity, and this ſtocke is to be ordered and diſpoſed by the advice and counſell of the ſageſt and graveſt Senators of this City.</p>
                  <p>Thirdly, to enable young be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginners to goe on chearfully in their callings, in workes of good husbandry, he hath left thirteene hundred pounds to bee lent to poore freemen of the company of Ironmongers, 100. pound a
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:119685:35"/> man upon good ſecurity, at 4. li. <hi>per centum</hi> for a yeare.</p>
                  <p>Fourthly, for the reliefe of poor helpleſſe children in Chriſt hoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pitall he hath given 500. pound To enlarge the hoſpitall of Saint <hi>Thomas</hi> in Southwark with more lodging for poore ſicke diſeaſed perſons, he hath given 1500. li. And for a further reliefe of the poore, blinde, lame, diſeaſed, and lunatique perſons in Bridewell, St. <hi>Bartholomewes,</hi> and Bethlehem Hoſpitalls, he hath given 300. li. <hi>viz.</hi> 100. li. to each.</p>
                  <p>Fiftly, for redemption of poor Captives under Turkiſh ſlavery, where they are inforced by cruell torments to forſake their Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, he hath given one thouſand
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:119685:35"/> pounds. And for the releaſe and reliefe of poore diſtreſſed priſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners that lye in miſerable bon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dage by meanes of mercileſſe cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditors, in nine priſons in and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout London, he hath given one thouſand pounds. What ſhall I ſay more? I am amazed at ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny charitable bequeſts of one man, for he hath not onely re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membred the Laity, but the Cler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gie alſo, not onely the valiant Souldiers, the Gentlemen of the Artillery Garden, with one hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred pounds towards their ſtock, and one hundred markes for a dinner or ſupper, becauſe he was once choſen a Colonell of this City: but poore honeſt preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Miniſters alſo, with 500. li.
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:119685:36"/> towards the ſupply of their ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſities, not to exceed 5. li. nor leſſe then 40. ſhillings a man, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he would nouriſh learning and religion, for he knew lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning to bee a maine prop to up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold religion in its purity, and therefore not to bee deſpiſed, as now it is, for the infirmities of ſome few men. And not onely mankinde in generall, but ſuch things as conduce to his honour and livelihood, this judicious charitable Gentleman hath thought on in the compoſure of his Teſtament, firſt to comfort and refreſh the poore deſtitute in cold weather, he hath follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed his fathers ſteps, and left 500. pounds for a further ſupply of a
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:119685:36"/> ſtocke of Coales, which his ſaid father Sir <hi>Thomas Cambel</hi> Knight, and ſometime Lord Maior of London began with three hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred pounds: ſecondly, to make wayes paſſable, to abridge long journeyes, and to eaſe labour, he hath left 250. pounds for the ere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of a new bridge over the Foord neere Wanſted in Eſſex: and laſt of al, that we as he ſhould delight to bee in the Church of God, which is the congregation of the faithfull, the houſe of pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, where with one heart wee ſhould heare God ſpeake unto us by his word, and wee unto him by humble confeſſion, earneſt ſupplication, and hearty thankſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giving, hee hath given one thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:119685:37"/> pounds towards the repaire of the mother Church the Cathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dral Church of Saint <hi>Paul,</hi> which evidently ſhowes he was a man that did approve all things in the worſhip of God ſhould bee de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent and in good order. And leſt he himſelfe ſhould forget any that were capable of charity, hee hath left the overplus of his eſtate (which by his computation will be ten thouſand pounds, if not impaired by bad debts, or other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe) in his Executors diſcretion to diſpoſe of in ſome ſuch piou and charitable worke or workes, thing or things, as they ſhall think fit, which I hope will bee to the glory of God, the reliefe of the poor, the honour of the deceaſed,
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:119685:37"/> and to the comfort and joy of the Executors themſelves. Yet I have not mentioned all his charitable Legacies, for I have not made re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation of 120. l. to 120. poor men in money or gownes, and 12. d. a piece for their dinner upon the day of his Funerall. 200. l. to poore beggars to avoid trouble on the ſame day. 200. l. to the poore of the Pariſhes of Saint <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters</hi> Poore, and Saint <hi>Olaves</hi> Jew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry London, and of Barking in Eſſex. Beſides 100. l. to the pari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhioners of the Pariſh of Saint <hi>Olaves</hi> Jewry, for their good will to erect his monument by his fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers and his brothers Maſter <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bert Cambel,</hi> late Alderman of London. And being he was ſo
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:119685:38"/> carefull for his honour while hee lived I thought it part of my duty to take ſome labour for the aug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentation therof now he is dead, which I could no better way per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme, then by publiſhing thoſe his unparalleled Legacies: for though that may bee more ſolid and durable, yet this my labour may be as profitable and uſefull for the ſtirring up of ſome chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table mens heart to doe workes of this nature. For if they be tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly juſt while they live, they will ſhew the fruits thereof at their death, becauſe ſuch men doe ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome any great worke of charity till their death, if they doe any then, as I have beene told by ſome; for every rich man is not
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:119685:38"/> as Sir <hi>Iames,</hi> becauſe hee brought Juſtice and Mercy with him from his cradle, charactered on his name.</p>
                  <p>Therefore I ceaſe to wonder that he hath left ſuch a paterne at his death, when his name which was given him preſently after his birth demonſtrated the ſame, as appeares in the Acroſticke ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes and Anagrams following, made by mee neare three yeares ſince, and preſented.</p>
                  <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="acrostic_poem">
                     <body>
                        <pb n="66" facs="tcp:119685:39"/>
                        <head>To his ever honoured Maſter.</head>
                        <opener>
                           <salute>Sir.</salute>
                        </opener>
                        <l>IUſt <hi>is the Lord, in all his waies,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>And mercifull unto the poore:</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Man likewiſe ſhould in all Aſſaies</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Ever be</hi> Juſt, <hi>but loving more:</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Such are rare birds, in theſe our daies</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Can ballance theſe, in all their waies.</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>And yet I doubt not, but ſome are</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>Mercifull, <hi>and</hi> righteous <hi>both:</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>But I feare they're very rare</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Ev'n ſuch to find, in ripefull growth</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Let's then with</hi> Juſtice, mercy <hi>joyne,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Leſt we be paid in the ſame coyne.</hi>
                        </l>
                     </body>
                  </floatingText>
                  <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="anagram-themed_poem">
                     <body>
                        <pb n="67" facs="tcp:119685:39"/>
                        <head>
                           <hi>Iames Cambel</hi> Anagrammatized, Se I came Balm.</head>
                        <l>AS Balm <hi>is of a fragrant ſent,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>So, are thoſe Graces God hath lent</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>
                              <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nto mankind; ſit to ſet forth</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Gods glory, and his ſervants worth.</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>As</hi> Balm <hi>apply'd well to a ſore</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Doth heale, and cure, ſo, are the poure</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Reliev'd, recur'd by</hi> Mercies <hi>oyle</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Which now I find ſprings in my ſoile:</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>Se I came Balm, <hi>for this ſame cauſe</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Ev'n to fullfill my Makers Lawes,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>That both my life, and death ſet forth,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>Juſtice, <hi>and</hi> Mercies <hi>royall worth.</hi>
                        </l>
                     </body>
                  </floatingText>
                  <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="anagram-themed_poem">
                     <body>
                        <head>Another ANNAGRAM. <hi>James Cambell,</hi> I came Blamles.</head>
                        <l>
                           <hi>NO man (but</hi> Chriſt) <hi>in this world e're could</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>I came (in) blamles, <hi>and ſo goe away.</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>My thoughts are pure, words holy, and workes ſay</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>From ſin originall, and actuall ſtaileſſe:</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>For ſins forbidden fruit</hi> Adam <hi>did eate,</hi> blamles</l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Hath caus'd his children crave ſin, as their meat.</hi>
                        </l>
                        <pb n="68" facs="tcp:119685:40"/>
                        <l>
                           <hi>So, that young babes no ſooner borne but cry,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>As feeling ſins thrall, and lifes miſery.</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>But yet I read in Gods moſt ſacred word,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Many were tearmed</hi> Righteous <hi>by the Lord,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Such were good</hi> Noah, Daniel, Job <hi>the</hi> Juſt,</l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Not that they were ſo, for they had a luſt</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>To do ill, ſome of their workes did ſhew it,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>But God in</hi> Mercy, <hi>let not's</hi> Juſtice <hi>know it,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>So now, as then, ſome righteous men there be</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Not innocent from ſin, to God; yet free</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>From foule, notorious, nefarious crimes,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Such as are now the Cuſtome of the times,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>To do their Neighbour wrong, the poore oppreſſe</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>And make a Trade of all ungodlyneſſe.</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>But, the true</hi> Innocent <hi>is like a child,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Who in all Actions is both meeke and mild,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>And though ſometimes, by hap, they goe aſtray</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>And wander little, in an unknowne Way;</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Then doth he make inquiry, and is ſorry,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>That he did ſo, his erring ſelfe miſearry;</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Likewiſe, ſometimes God doth his grace reſtrain</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>From rareſt Saints, to ſhew they are but vaine</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Wiithout his aid; alſo to ſee and try</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>What bidden Graces, in their hearts do lie.</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>So, fell King</hi> David, Peter, <hi>and Saint</hi> Paul</l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>To humble them, us to Repentance call,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>In which reſpests (by Chriſt) ſome men may ſay</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>I come (in) blamles, <hi>and ſo goe away.</hi>
                        </l>
                     </body>
                  </floatingText>
                  <pb n="69" facs="tcp:119685:40"/>
                  <p>Now conſider, I pray, if what <hi>David</hi> ſpake in another ſenſe, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 85. 10, 11. verſes, may not bee truly ſaid of Sir <hi>Iames Cambel, Mercy and Truth are met together, Righteouſneſſe and Peace have kiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed each other: Truth ſhall flouriſh out of the earth, and Righteouſneſſe hath looked downe from heaven.</hi> One<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in ſtead of Truth reade Juſtice in the 10. verſe, and Mercy in the 11. verſe, and then 'tis plaine e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough that mercy ſhall ſpring or bud out of the earth, that is, as I apply it Sir <hi>Iames Cambels</hi> name was given him by earthly pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents, ſo it ſprung out of the earth, and that ſignifies mercy, as is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſpecified in the Anagram, <hi>Se I came balm: and Righteouſnes
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:119685:41"/> hath looked downe from heaven,</hi> that is, the Sun of Righteouſneſſe hath infuſed the Graces of his holy Spirit into his heart to doe righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe, as in his life, ſo at his death: and that likewiſe may be applyed to the Anagram on his name, <hi>I came blamles,</hi> ſo that it is evident by theſe Anagrams and Acroſticke verſes, that in Sir <hi>Iames Cambel</hi> Juſtice and Mercy met to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, according to this ſaying of the Prophet <hi>David,</hi> for now I ſhall not need to change the words in either verſe, for Truth, which is <hi>Fides,</hi> as <hi>Tremelius</hi> tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lates it, is the root from whence juſtice and Mercy ſpring: and without juſtice and mercy, faith is dead, and truth is falſhood.
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:119685:41"/> But if theſe two branches of Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy and Juſtice ſpring from the root of a true, lively, and juſtifying faith, the fruit that they beare will bee peace of conſcience, and joy in the holy Ghoſt. Thus will I ſing with holy <hi>David,</hi> as in a ſpirituall ſenſe, ſo in remembrance of my late ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noured Maſter, <hi>Mercy and Truth have met together, Righteouſneſſe and Peace have ki<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>ed each other, Truth ſhal flouriſh out of the earth, and Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe hath looked downe from heaven.</hi> Therefore I will conclude with theſe verſes following.</p>
                  <div type="elegy">
                     <pb n="72" facs="tcp:119685:42"/>
                     <l>JVſtice <hi>and</hi> Mercy <hi>were at great debate,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Who ſhould in Sir</hi> James <hi>moſt predominate:</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>True Faith came in, and ſaid, it was moſt meet</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>That</hi> Mercy, <hi>ſhe, ſhould have the upper ſeate:</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>For ſhe's the Queene of Grace, and for that cauſe</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>She is to moderate Gods Righteous Lawes.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>So 'twas concluded to appeaſe the brall,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Sweet, lovely</hi> Mercy <hi>ſhould be principall:</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>For from true ſaving</hi> Faith, <hi>Sir</hi> James <hi>did bring</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Mercy, <hi>and</hi> Juſtice <hi>like a living ſpring</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Of heavenly water, to refreſh and glad</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>All <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ood mens hearts, his loſſe maks me full ſad<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                        </hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>For</hi> Juſtice <hi>ceaſed with his vitall breath;</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>But</hi> Mercy <hi>will endure long after death.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>And ſure his</hi> Juſtice, <hi>and his Pious waies,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Shall ever live to his eternall praiſe</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>For an example<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> though in act it ceaſe,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>But</hi> Mercy <hi>now in act doth ſtill increaſe</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>And ſhewes her beauty, in moſt brave array</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>To poore diſtreſſed people whoſe decay</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>She greatly pittying, doth give ſupply</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>To their neceſſities, and miſery.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Oh had I art I would ſet forth the praiſe</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Of Sir</hi> James Cambels <hi>pious, righteous waies;</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>But being my learning's ſmall conclude will I</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>In mournfull Epitaph and Elegie.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </div>
                  <div type="acrostic_elegy">
                     <pb n="55" facs="tcp:119685:42"/>
                     <head>An Acroſtick Elegie.</head>
                     <l>
                        <hi>IF</hi> loſſe <hi>of</hi> friends <hi>be cauſe of griefe; then I,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>And all good people have ſome cauſe to cry;</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Many good men there are, I hope, but yet</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Ev'n as Sir</hi> James <hi>was, are full hard to get<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                        </hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Such was his</hi> Prudence, <hi>and his</hi> Pious care,</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Could order all things well, which to declare</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>And ſhow, his vertues all, in e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ch degree</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Might maſe the</hi> Muſes nine, <hi>and much more me.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>But this I doe, by my unskilfull Art</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Eternally, to ſhew my thankfull heart.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Loſſes <hi>I have, how can I chuſe but cry?</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Loſſe <hi>hath this City, can our eyes be dry?</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Yet though he's</hi> loſt to us <hi>he's</hi> found in heav'n<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Becauſe his</hi> Mamon <hi>to the poore is giv'n<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                        </hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Whoſe</hi> Friends <hi>are there, for to receive and keep</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>His bleſſed ſoule, although his body ſleep.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <epigraph>
                        <q>Our Friend <hi>Lazarus</hi> ſleepeth <bibl>
                              <hi>John</hi> 11. 11.</bibl>
                        </q>
                        <q>Pretious, in the ſight of the Lord, is the death of his Saints. <bibl>
                              <hi>Pſal.</hi> 116. 15.</bibl>
                        </q>
                        <q>Bleſſed are the dead, that die in the Lord, even ſo ſaith the Spirit, for they reſt from their Labours; and their works follow them. <bibl>
                              <hi>Apoc.</hi> 14. 13.</bibl>
                        </q>
                     </epigraph>
                  </div>
                  <div type="acrostic_epitaph">
                     <pb n="74" facs="tcp:119685:43"/>
                     <head>An Acroſtick Epitaph.</head>
                     <lg>
                        <l>
                           <hi>IN this ſame</hi> Casket <hi>lies a</hi> Jewell <hi>rare</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>And will you know the great worth of the ſame<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>
                           </hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Mark well theſe words, his vertu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>s paſſe compare,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Eternall honour, ſhall raiſe to his name.</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Soe</hi> Juſt, <hi>and equall were his vertuous waies</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Conſtant in Prastice thereof, all his daies.</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>A man that alwaies ſtood for common good,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Made him belev'd of all men, far<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>e and neere.</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>By</hi> Prudent Juſtice, <hi>he all vice withſtood,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Equall to him, where ſhall we find his peere?</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Lo now hee's laid up, in this earthen mould</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>Like as a Jewell, in a caſe of gold.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>
                           <hi>This is the monument upon his name</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Which I erected by my ruſtick quill,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>But there's a thing of coſt, and curious frame</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Rarely contrived, by induſtrious skill:</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>In</hi> Olaves Jewry Church <hi>it is to ſtand,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>A more compleater thing's not in this land.</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>Sir Iames <hi>is there to lie in ſtately port,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Clad all in armour, like a</hi> Martiall man.</l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Like a grave</hi> Senator, <hi>in gallant ſort</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Hee's wrapt in robes, even as an</hi> Alderman,</l>
                        <l>Courage, <hi>and</hi> Wiſedome <hi>in him did remaine,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>And now hee's dead, this Figure ſhews the ſame.</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Moſt</hi> Juſt, <hi>and equall were his P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>ous waies,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <pb n="75" facs="tcp:119685:43"/>
                        <l>
                           <hi>And therefore at his feet doth</hi> Juſtice <hi>ſtand,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>And at his head, to his eternall praiſe,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>Mercy <hi>is fixed with her Babe in hand.</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>In him ſterne</hi> Juſtice, <hi>did ſweet mercy meet,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>And now hee's dead they ſtand at's head and fe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>t.</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Cloſe by him</hi> kneeles his Lady <hi>much lamenting</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>The loſſe of her</hi> deare Pheer, this pious man;</l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>A true Character, lively repreſenting,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>The ſad Condition of this good woman:</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>For, ſhee is truely like the</hi> Turtle dove,</l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Dayly bewayling the loſſe of her Love.</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>But let her ceaſe to grieve, for from above</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Behold an Angell bright, deſcending downe,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>And for the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>ood deeds, done by her true Love,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>With Laurell Garland will his Temples crowne<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>s</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>To learne by their examples all men may,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>Juſtice, <hi>and</hi> Mercy <hi>drawes the Vaile away.</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Therfore is</hi> Fame, <hi>and</hi> Time <hi>his Arms ſupporters</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>To ſhew to all that in the world doe live,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>That vertuous Actions cannot want reporters:</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>For</hi> Fame, <hi>will</hi> Time <hi>to ſuch man ſurely give,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>That in good works doe ſpend the pain, and time,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>And, now I did intend to ceaſe my Rime:</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>But that</hi> Fame <hi>calls to ſhew the coſt and skill</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Of this rare ſtructures Fabricke, ſtately brave,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Contrived and compoſed; but my quill</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Is blunt and dull, for I no learning have;</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Therefore I'le ceaſe, and ſay 'tis rich and faire,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Marble, and Alablaſter carv'd moſt rare.</hi>
                        </l>
                     </lg>
                  </div>
                  <div type="poem">
                     <pb n="76" facs="tcp:119685:44"/>
                     <head>Of the favour of man.</head>
                     <l>FAvour <hi>of great men, in this world's a</hi> Flower</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Hardly in long time got, loſt in an hower.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>He, then that builds his hope upon a prop</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>That is ſo weake, muſt needs expect it drop:</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>For, though he ſpend his time, his care, his skill,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>In dunging, dreſſing, keeping it from ill</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>That might annoy it, yet the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>eate of</hi> raſhneſſe</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Cold of</hi> neglect, <hi>or wind of its owne</hi> harſhneſſe</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>May wither, nip, or blow it quite away,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Such is the fruite of ſuch a rotten ſtay.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Oh! happie then, in this world's he that well</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Can live, and breath without this flowers ſmell.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>But there is none on earth, that truely can.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Live, or ſubſiſt without the helpe of man:</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>For Lawyers live upon their Clients fees,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>And ſome rich men, on poore mens miſeries.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>So Clergie men, upon the lay depend,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>And each to other muſt needs be a friend:</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>For, ſellers live upon the buyers gaines,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>And rich men do grow proud, on poore folks pains.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Why then, ſhould I thinke it more ſtange to me</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>When I ſee others i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> the ſame degree:</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>A bad bargaine, ſometimes hath the buyer,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>And poore men are not alwaies paid their <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>yer:</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>For, though ſomtimes, I do diſpleaſur<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> gaine</hi>
                     </l>
                     <pb n="77" facs="tcp:119685:44"/>
                     <l>
                        <hi>By ſome raſh word, or deed, which breeds my p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ine,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Yet: after, I am ſorry, and doe feare</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>How I do in the ſelfe ſame kinde appeare:</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>So though to ſome</hi> Favour <hi>a</hi> Flower <hi>be,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Yet unto me, it is a well growne</hi> Tree,</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Which I will labour for to keep and cherriſh.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>That neither me, nor mine may come to perriſh<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                        </hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>And therefore never will I ceaſe to pray</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>That God may guide me, in faire vertues way:</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>For therein ſurely, I ſhall finde the Grace</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>And</hi> Favour <hi>of good men, as time and place</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Shall give occaſion; in this hope I'le reſt</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Not doubting, but i'th end I ſhalbe bleſt</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>With all ſuch things, as God ſees good for me</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>According to my calling, and degree.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </div>
                  <div type="double_acrostic_elegy">
                     <head>An Acroſtick Elegie, ON The deaths of the right worſhipful Mr. <hi>Anthony Abdie,</hi> Alderman of London, who departed this tranſitorie life, on Thurſday the 10. of <hi>September,</hi> 1640. and Miſtris <hi>Abigail</hi> his wife, who died the Friday before,</head>
                     <l>
                        <hi>ALL men are borne to die, that is moſt true;</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>No man can hinder death, not I, nor you,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Though we were wiſe, rich, luſty, ſtorng and faier</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Hee's ſuch a Sergeant, for Bribes hee'll not care:</hi>
                     </l>
                     <pb n="78" facs="tcp:119685:45"/>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Oh! hee's too cruell; neither man, nor wife</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>No King, nor Keyſar can make him ſpare life:</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Yet, why ſhould he ſo cruell be to theſe?</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Alas! could not the wife alone him pleaſe</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>But muſt he preſently the husband take?</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Did death think much, he ſhould his wife for ſake?</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>In Hymens day, they promis'd ne're to part</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Ev'n unt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ll Death did ſtrike them to the heart;</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>And ſo they did performe that ſolemne vow,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>By living both together untill now.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>In thirty yeares, ſhe was his wedded wife,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>God made them rich, in bleſſings of this life;</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>And ſo, to make them happy, children ten</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>I know they had, three maids, the other men,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Like Olive plants about their Table ſpread,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>And two of them are maried, three are dead:</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>But heer's the cauſe of this my riming quill,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Death, at one in<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                              <desc>••</desc>
                           </gap>ant ſhould this couple kill</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>In midſt of joy, this makes me mourne, yet learne,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Ev'n as to poore folke, ſo, to rich 'Death's ſterne<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                        </hi>
                     </l>
                  </div>
                  <div type="acrostic_epitaph">
                     <head>An Acroſtick Epitaph.</head>
                     <l>
                        <hi>ALL mortall men that by us paſſe</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Note well, conſider, life's as graſſe</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>That ſeemeth freſh and faire all day,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Hew'n down by death, ſoon <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ades away<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                        </hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>On earthly things ſet not your love,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Nature's adverſe to things above<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                        </hi>
                     </l>
                     <pb n="79" facs="tcp:119685:45"/>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Yeeld therefore unto God your heart,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>And after death you'll feele no ſmart;</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>But, if you do in ſinne delight,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Death then will make you feele his might</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>In dolour great, in pain ſo fell,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Ev'n as the torments are in hell.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>And thus wee ſhew what we do find,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>By our example bend your mind</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>(In wiſdomes ſchoole) to learne, and know</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Gods will; and in good workes it ſhow</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>As we two did, and made it ſhine</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>In Pious deeds, in Love divine;</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Like to the Turtle and his mate,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Alwaies we liv'd in quiet ſtate,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>But cruell death with his ſharp knife,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Did mow the Graſſe of my wives life:</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>I followed her, then ſeaſe to weepe,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Ev'n as in Bed, we ſweetely ſleepe.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <p>They were both buried together upon the firſt day of <hi>October,</hi> 1640. in the Pariſh Church of Saint <hi>Andrew</hi> Underſhaft.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="epitaph">
                     <pb facs="tcp:119685:46"/>
                     <head>IN MEMORIAM,</head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>PRudentiſsimi Senator is</hi> Jacobi Cambel <hi>Mil<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> tis nuper Major i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> Civitatis Londinenſis, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>tea Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nior is Aldermani &amp; unius Pacis Iuſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciarum in Civitate predicta. Major is inſuper Privilegiorum Civitatis Weſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monaſterii, Praeſidis Hoſpitalis ſeu Xenodochii Divi</hi> Thomae <hi>in Burgo Southwarke &amp; Galicorum Mercatorum Rector is Memoriale</hi> Edwardi Brown <hi>eidem devotiſsimi dum vixit Ratio Operis.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="poem">
                     <l>TO make my Sun and Moon ſhine cleare,</l>
                     <l>My Starre and Mete or thus appeare</l>
                     <l>Within bright favours firmament:</l>
                     <l>I hope my time is not miſpent.</l>
                     <l>In uſeles workes, in fruitleſſe pain,</l>
                     <l>For little Credit, much leſſe gaine,</l>
                     <l>Becauſe my Maſters praiſe and worth</l>
                     <l>In theſe Books like wiſe is ſet forth<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                     </l>
                     <l>Yet howſoever, I know this</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Spes &amp; Proemium in Coelis.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </div>
                  <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               </div>
               <div type="illustration">
                  <pb facs="tcp:119685:46"/>
                  <p>
                     <figure>
                        <figDesc>engraving representing the tomb of James Cambell by William Marshall</figDesc>
                        <p>
                           <hi>In Memoriam Prudentiſsimi Senator Iacobi Cambell Militis &amp;c.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>
                           <hi>For prudent juſtice, and true Piety Here lyes a Patern; pray obſerve him well And for true Love without Hypocriſy He was a Mirror: In his soule did dwell True Faith, the Mother of the Graces three Of Juſtice, Holynes, and Charity. So though his Corps ſeemeth herein to ly His Virtues rare, ſhall live &amp; never dy.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </figure>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:119685:47"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:119685:47"/>
                  <p>A METEOR. OR, Briefe and pleaſant MEDITATIONS Of the Providence of God toward His CHOSEN: And <hi>Of the education of Children.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <figure>
                        <figDesc>printer's device of William Ley or Lee, a circle featuring the heavens (stars, a meteor, the sun and the moon), clouds, rain and the sea</figDesc>
                        <head>
                           <q>Conſcientia bona non timet pericula.</q>
                        </head>
                     </figure>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="epigraph">
                  <pb facs="tcp:119685:48"/>
                  <head>EXODUS 9. 23. 24.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>And the Lord rained haile upon the Land of</hi> Egypt, <hi>ſo there was haile, and fire mingled with haile very grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vous, ſuch as there was none like it in all the Land of</hi> Egypt <hi>ſince it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came a Nation.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="dedication">
                  <pb facs="tcp:119685:48"/>
                  <head>To His judicious-loving, and ever-honoured Maſter, the right Worſhipfull Sir <hi>Iames Cambel</hi> Knight and ſenior Alderman of London, &amp;c.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>Ngratitude<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                     </hi> as it ſtops the ſtreame of Gods mercie from deſcending upon his people, ſo, it dams up the current of charitable mens bounty towards the poore; for hee that is not thankfull for former benefits, is unworthy to receive any future good. In conſideration whereof, I, having recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved from your Worſhip many undeſerved favours for the ſpace of theſe 16. yeares ſervice under you, did bethinke with my ſelfe which way I might really expreſſe
<pb facs="tcp:119685:49"/> my thankfull heart for the ſame. But when <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> conſidered my owne penury and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſufficiency for the performance of any worke, worthy your <hi>judicious</hi> and grave inſpection; I was afraid that in ſtead of favour, I might incurre d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſpleaſure: And therefore reſted my ſelfe in contemplation of m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ne owne workes<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> which after ſome ple<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſing<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> paine I h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>d conce<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ved in my minde. But having oft obſerved you rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding divers famous mens writ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ngs, as <hi>Perkins, Greenham<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>,</hi> and others, the latchet of whoſe ſhooes I am unworthy to unlooſe<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> I am bold to intreat your Worſhip not to d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſd<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ne to peruſe theſe imperfect works of your unworthy ſervant, for there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in you ſhall ſee how I have ſpent moſt p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rt of my ſpare t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>me ſince I have beene a wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dower. For I having according to my ſmall ability patched the fin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> ſpun cloth of the Prince of Poets <hi>Du Bar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>as</hi> ſmooth e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loquence, with my home ſpun rags, and courſe materials, and framed thereof a piece of rough <hi>Poetry,</hi> for my retired thoughts to repoſe in. I was imboldened to preſent the ſame to your Worſhip in pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate,
<pb facs="tcp:119685:49"/> as a token or pledge of my gratitude for your former favours extended towards me. Now as the Tw<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ns did ſtrive and ſtruggle within the wombe of <hi>Rebecca,</hi> and the firſt borne was no ſconer brought forth, but the younger followed, taking his Brother faſt hold by the heele: ſo my <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuall World</hi> ſo cloſely followed thoſe <hi>Poe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticall Meditations,</hi> that I could not reſt ſatisfied in my mind till I had likewiſe brought it forth. And ſo, after ſome la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour and travell in Engliſh Authors for your Worſhip knowes I am no Linguiſt<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> I have brought it to m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>turity, and placed the younger before the elder, as <hi>Jacob</hi> was by his father preferred before <hi>Eſau;</hi> But the firſt being not approved but greatly diſl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ked contrary to my expectation, and the opinion of men, riper in judgment then my ſelfe, upon the 17. of April laſt I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived the ſame againe<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> to ſatisfie the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire of ſome, to have the peruſall thereof. Before which time, as I informed your Worſhip. I had finiſhed my <hi>Annuall World</hi> to the ſecond ſtory, and therefore would not leave off in the midſt of my
<pb facs="tcp:119685:50"/> worke, contrary to your Worſhips direction, who adviſed me to ſurceaſe and leave, leſt I might come to be as ſome have been, and receive ſuch puniſhment as <hi>Phaeton</hi> brought upon himſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>fe, by being too buſie in things above my learning and ſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ength. But by the inablement of Gods ſpirit in me, I have, as I writ, notwithſtanding all my other affaires, given vent to this <hi>new wine,</hi> which otherwiſe might have dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nified the <hi>veſſell.</hi> Now becauſe the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer had no reliſh in your palate, I was a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fraid that my <hi>Annuall World</hi> would have proved diſpleaſing to your taſte, and therefore, having fully finiſhed that I am adviſed to put them both into print, and to dedicate the ſame not onely to your ſelfe, but to all the Senators of this famous City, of whom you are the moſt ancient, for God hath prolonged your life, to enjoy that ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable title of <hi>Pater Civitatis,</hi> and I doe humbly acknowledge, that you are <hi>Alum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus mens.</hi> Therefore you being the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter of the time which I have borrowed to accompliſh all theſe workes: All my la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours and endeavours are properly yours,
<pb facs="tcp:119685:50"/> comming from the ſweet and wholſome nouriſhment they receive from you, hoping that as the little chamber, which the affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctionate <hi>Shunamite</hi> prepared for the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet <hi>Eliſha,</hi> was more accepted, th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>n the gold, ſilver, and changes of rayment offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red by <hi>Naaman</hi> the <hi>Syrian:</hi> ſo theſe un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>learned workes of mine, being nothing elſe but an expreſsion of my affection, will bee more acceptable now in your old age then a preſent of greater coſt and worth. For in my apprehenſion as your body declines to the earth, ſo, your ſoule aſcends into hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, and therefore it is that you disburden your ſelfe of worldly cares, by diſpoſing of your ſubſtance while you live, to your owne and my Ladies kindred, in <hi>Felix</hi> and <hi>Clayhall,</hi> which evidently ſhowes that you are out of love with earthly fading happineſſe. That you may more freely ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply your minde in ſeeking after heavenly and everlaſting Treaſure, by contempla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and meditation of the wondrous works of God; which is<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> from many learned mens workes, briefly compriſed in theſe Bookes, the firſt as your Worſhip knowes, I
<pb facs="tcp:119685:51"/> compared to a <hi>Starre,</hi> as <hi>Orion,</hi> and the <hi>Pleiades,</hi> diſaſterous and ominous to fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warne me, (as an evident ſigne) of ſome enſuing tempeſt: or as <hi>Caſtor</hi> and <hi>Pol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lux</hi> fortunate and ſucceſſefull, to lead me (or a token that I ſhall arrive) in a ſafe harbour. The ſecond I compared to the <hi>Moone,</hi> becauſe it is moſt part borrowed from that glorious <hi>Sun</hi> divine <hi>Du Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tas.</hi> And the laſt to the <hi>Sunne,</hi> becauſe it treats of divine Meditations through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the yeare, as <hi>Sol illuminat mundum.</hi> Now to make theſe lights ſhine the clearer; I have framed this <hi>Meteor;</hi> for my <hi>Star,</hi> that was not firmly fixed, my <hi>Moone</hi> I have changed, but my <hi>Sunne</hi> will ſhine the brighter, after this foggy and drowſie m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſt hath diſplayed it ſelfe; for after a tempeſt comes faire weather, and the <hi>Sun</hi> ſhines pleaſantly after a ſhowre of raine. All theſe fruitleſſe labours of my braine I am bold to preſent to your Worſhip not out of any hope to draw any of your earthly ſubſtance from y<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>u, neither doe I hereby cog, flatter, or ſooth you, or any other, in hope to get ſome great preferment thereby,
<pb facs="tcp:119685:51"/> for I ſcorne ſuch flatteries, neither doe I herein meddle with other folkes matters its enough for me to looke to my ſelfe, and my owne buſineſſe. For throughout theſe Bookes I ſtill reflect upon my ſelfe, know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing very well the old ſaying, That every tub muſt ſtand upon his owne bottome, and every mans labour will either praiſe or diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>praiſe the workman. But I onely writ them for the eaſe of my minde, and to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe my gratitude for all your favours extendea towar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> me. Therefore I am not fearfull who hath the peruſall hereof, for I hope it will hold triall, beare touch and prove good met all. Yet as it is too well knowne I am farre unworthy to appropri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate to my ſelfe the laborious induſtry and care of <hi>J<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>cob,</hi> or the wiſedome and ſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of <hi>David,</hi> ſo I would not have your Worſhip ſurm<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſe, that I meane you have or ever had the venemous qualities of the <hi>Serpent,</hi> or the ſharpe cr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ggineſſe of the <hi>Rocke,</hi> which is likewiſe very well known to the contrary But becauſe I made uſe of thoſe ex<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>mples in ſome of my writings, for which I feare your Worſhip tooke d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taſte
<pb facs="tcp:119685:52"/> I am bold to cleare my ſelfe thus: That as in reſpect of my long ſervice un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der you, I may in ſome ſort compare my ſelfe to <hi>Jacob,</hi> and in regard of my penury be like unto <hi>David;</hi> ſo for providentiall wiſedome you are as a <hi>Serpent,</hi> and for ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lid gravitie as a <hi>Rocke.</hi> Therefore in confidence of your favourable acceptance, I humbly preſent this, with my ſelfe, and all my endeavours, to your Worſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ps ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice, never ceaſing to pray, that God would ſo bleſſe you, and your loving Conſort, my vertuous Lady; with the graces of his bleſſed Spirit, and temporall bleſsings in this life<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>t you may enjoy eternall hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſſe in the life to come: and will ever remaine,</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>Your humble and gratefull ſervant, Edw. Browne.</signed>
                     <date>29. Octob. 1640.</date>
                  </closer>
               </div>
               <div type="frontispiece">
                  <pb facs="tcp:119685:52"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:119685:53"/>
                  <p>
                     <figure>
                        <figDesc>engraved portrait of Edward Browne seated at a table, writing, with two children nearby, by William Marshall</figDesc>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Spes &amp; Praemium in Coelis.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>
                           <hi>In Hevenly Light I will Delight.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>
                           <hi>My Portion ſure Will ever dure.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <byline>W. M. Sculp:</byline>
                     </figure>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="poem">
                  <pb facs="tcp:119685:53"/>
                  <head>A Phantaſtick Lover.</head>
                  <l>
                     <hi>BEhold, how vainly I have ſpent my time<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                     </hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>By making Books, in fruitleſſe proſe, and rime</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>To win a Damſells love, with Pen and Inke,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>I wonder why, I ſhould ſo fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>dly thinke</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Some win their Miſtris by ſweet words and rimes,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>But ſuch are rare to find, in theſe our times;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Others like</hi> Jupiter <hi>on</hi> Danaes <hi>Tower</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Do purchaſſe love, in ſuch a golden ſhower,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>But moſt, and that's the way thy Love to meete</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>As</hi> Par<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s, Hellen; Mars <hi>did</hi> Venus <hi>greete;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Theſe things I know<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and yet my troubled mind</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Did urge me to make Books<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> true Love to find</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>In Vertues breaſt; but not for forme, or pelfe,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Becauſe like</hi> Jacob <hi>I compar'd my ſelfe,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>That, as he having neither houſe nor lands,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>By Gods great Providence, became two bands<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                     </hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>So, I that have been very weake and poore</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Might come in better ſtate I was before,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Did thinke to g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>t a</hi> Rachel <hi>for my mate,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>And by my child<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>n come in double ſtate;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>But I'm not like to him, neither is ſhe</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Like</hi> Rachel, <hi>faire though</hi> Bright <hi>her name may be,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Neither have I ſerv'd</hi> Laban, <hi>though 'tis true</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>In eighteene yeares, eleven pound paid my due</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>For Salarie, my bargain was no more,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Why ſhould I care, or too much grieve therefore;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:119685:54"/>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Yet, ſuch like wordly loſſes breedeth pain</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Vnto mans mind, and doth much hurt the brain;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>But I'll give thankes to God, for he hath brought</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>My Labour to an end, for ſtill I thought</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Whether I loſt or got, my hope was this</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>To have Gods Love: for</hi> Proemium in Coelis.</l>
               </div>
               <div type="poem" subtype="to_the__reader">
                  <head>Liber ad Lectorem.</head>
                  <l>
                     <hi>REad to the end,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Leſt I offend.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Pray marke, and Judge,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Before you grudge.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>And you ſhall find</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>How I'm inclind,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>To ſhew the crimes</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Of theſe laſt times.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>In</hi> Labans <hi>caſe,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>And</hi> Nab<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ls <hi>face;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>How</hi> Eſaus <hi>Pride,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>May be eſpide,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>And, how to find</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>A vertuous mind.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Therefore I pray</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Caſt ſpleene away.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Then read with eaſe,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>I ſhall you pleaſe.</hi>
                  </l>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div type="tract">
                  <pb n="1" facs="tcp:119685:54"/>
                  <head>A METEOR. OR, A briefe and pleaſant Meditation of the Providence of God towards his choſen: and of the edu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation of children.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He conſideration of the power of natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall love in the heart of Mankinde, hath of late induced me to write of divers things gathered out of the word of God, and other writings. But now having by the aſſiſting grace of the Almighty, fully finiſhed three
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:119685:55"/> Bookes, <hi>viz. Liber Amoris, Sacred P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>emes,</hi> and <hi>an Annuall World,</hi> I thought good, for the eaſe of my minde, as my <hi>Vultimum vale</hi> to writing of ſuch my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteries, too high for my capacity to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrate, to ſet downe theſe confuſed notions following. The firſt ſhall bee the conſideration of Gods Providence towards his choſen, in the examples of <hi>Iacob</hi> and <hi>David.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>In the ſecond place, becauſe I began to write of the love of young men, I will conclude with the love of old men to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards their children, in the examples of <hi>Iſaac</hi> and <hi>Iacob.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>In the firſt I will ſhow, how God turned a <hi>Serpent,</hi> to a <hi>ſtaffe of ſupport,</hi> for the preſervation of <hi>Iacob,</hi> and alſo how he made <hi>water</hi> to flow out of the <hi>hard Rocke<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                     </hi> for the reliefe and refreſhment of <hi>David.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>In the ſecond, I will declare and ſet forth, how aged parents (as in a glaſſe) may ſee how to place and fix their love towards their children and kindred. In <hi>Iſaacs</hi> love towards <hi>Eſau,</hi> and in <hi>Iacobs</hi>
                     <pb n="3" facs="tcp:119685:55"/> love towards <hi>Ioſeph.</hi> But becauſe all theſe things are directly againſt the worldly-wiſe Politicians, eſpecially in theſe dangerous dayes, who are in beſt eſteeme, I thought it more ſafe for me, to deſiſt and ſtay my pen, leſt I too roughly handling that which is <hi>Noli me tangere,</hi> might incur juſt reproofe and puniſhment for my labour. Yet be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe I mentioned theſe things in <hi>Libro Amo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> is,</hi> and other writings, and for that I doe not intend to ſtray from the Text of Scripture, but keepe cloſe to the ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuine ſenſe of the word of God, ſo that none may find fault therewith, but they that applying it to themſelves find their galled backs hurt, or too groſly toucht. I will not feare to goe forward, leſt it ſhould be ſaid, I have written that I was not able to make good. Therefore I will declare how the <hi>Serpent</hi> became a <hi>Rod,</hi> or <hi>ſtaffe of ſupport to Iacob.</hi> It is plain that I doe not meane that which was firſt a Rod, then a Serpent, and laſt of all a Rod againe in the hand of <hi>Moſes:</hi> nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther doe I meane the Serpent that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiled
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:119685:56"/> our firſt parents, or any other na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall Serpent. But I will write of <hi>La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ban,</hi> as a Serpent: and to prove that hee had the properties and qualities that are in a Serpent, and ſo very well com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared thereunto, I will divide him in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to three parts: firſt his <hi>head,</hi> ſecondly his <hi>skinne,</hi> and laſt of all his <hi>ſting.</hi> Firſt, that <hi>Laban</hi> had the head of a Serpent, <hi>viz.</hi> he was wiſe politique, and very crafty, is plaine. The Scripture teſtifies that the Serpent was more ſubtile then any beaſt of the field. And Chriſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horteth us to be wiſe as Serpents, both for the defence of our ſelves, and of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence of our enemies. The Serpents wiſedome conſiſts in foure things. Firſt, in the Spring ſhe caſts off her old skin, and puts on a new: ſecondly, ſhe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fends her head above all things: third<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, ſhe ſtops her eares at the voice of the charmer: and laſtly, ſhe alwayes carries poiſon in her mouth, which ſhee expo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth before ſhe drinkes. The applicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of this ſerpentine wiſedome I paſſe by. But affirme, that politicall wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:119685:56"/> for every man to bee provident. Firſt, for his owne ſoules ſalvation: ſecondly, for his owne bodies health: and thirdly, for the welfare of his own family, is ſo far from reproofe, that it is worthy high commendation. And chiefly the firſt. But how <hi>Laban</hi> was thus qualified, there's the quaere. For firſt, it's plaine he was not ſo wiſe as he ſhould bee, hee did want that which is the true wiſedome, <hi>viz. fiduciall know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of the true God.</hi> Hee went aſtray out of the right way, according as his father <hi>Nahor</hi> before him had done and worſhipped Images, the worke of mens hands, wood and ſtone. For when <hi>Ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chel</hi> had ſtolne ſome of thoſe Images, he did exclaime againſt <hi>Iacob,</hi> that hee had ſtolne his gods: ſo when be made a covenant of peace with <hi>Iacob,</hi> he con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed it with an oath, taking the god of <hi>Nahor</hi> to be his witneſſe. So that its plaine he was an <hi>idolater,</hi> and therefore not wiſe for his ſoules ſalvation, for no Idolater ſhall enter into the kingdome of heaven.</p>
                  <pb n="6" facs="tcp:119685:57"/>
                  <p>Secondly, for the welfare of his own body, there is no queſtion but that hee as all worldly minded men are, and all godly men ſhould, was carefull to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve that, if he did not take too much care thereupon.</p>
                  <p>And laſt of all, for the proviſion of his owne family, he was very carefull, and he that is not ſo, is worſe then an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidell, even worſe then <hi>Laban,</hi> for he was very covetous, and that appeares throughout the ſtory: for when <hi>Iacob</hi> had told him his arrand, <hi>viz.</hi> that hee had purchaſed the birthright of his el<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der brother, that he had obtained the bleſſing of his father, that hee was ſent to him by his father and mother for a wife, that he had ſeene a viſion by the way; and having according to his own agreement performed ſeven yeares for <hi>Rachel,</hi> he out of a baſe covetous deſire, becauſe hee would not loſe the benefit of <hi>Iacobs</hi> ſervice, cheated him with blear-ey'd <hi>Lea,</hi> and made him ſerve 7. yeares more for <hi>Rachel;</hi> for he thought, if <hi>Iacob</hi> had obtained his love, he would
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:119685:57"/> have ſerved him no longer. Therefore finding that God bleſſed him for <hi>Iacobs</hi> ſake, and as <hi>Iacob</hi> told him, ſaying, for the little that thou hadſt before I came, is increaſed to a multitude, was very un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>willing to part with <hi>Iacob,</hi> and therefore agreed with him upon a certaine bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine of wages. But when hee ſaw that <hi>Iacob</hi> got too much that way, he abrid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged him of that, and changed his wages ten times: like many covetous maſters in theſe dayes, that for feare their ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants ſhould thrive under them, grow proud, or fit for better ſervices, doe what they can, as wel in abridging them of that which is their juſt due, as ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times in thoſe things they may get without them, I meane without any da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage or great trouble to them, as a word of their mouth, a note of their hand, or in performing the will of the dead. But I have no cauſe to complain in this particular, for I doe humbly ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge, my Maſter hath and doth more good for me then I deſerve. Yet I preſume to touch thoſe Maſters that
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:119685:58"/> care not for their owne credit or their ſervants good. Therefore leaving the politique head of <hi>Laban,</hi> I come to his skinne. The skin of a Serpent is beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifull and gliſtering, and ſeemeth more amiable then hurtfull; and <hi>Laban</hi> as his name ſignifies <hi>White,</hi> the moſt beauti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full colour, ſo he ſeemed to bee a very faire dealing honeſt man, as by his ora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to <hi>Iacob</hi> appeareth, in theſe words: <hi>What haſt thou done? thou haſt even ſtoln away my heart, and carried away my daughters as though they had beene taken captives with the ſword: wherefore didſt thou flie ſo ſecretly, and ſteale away from me, and didſt not tell me, that I might have ſent thee forth with mirth, and with ſongs, with Timbrell, and with Harpe: But thou haſt not ſuffered mee to kiſſe my ſonnes and my daughters. Now thou haſt done fooliſhly in a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ng ſo: yet though thou w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>nteſt away becauſe thou greatly longeſt after thy fathers houſe, wherefore haſt thou ſtolne away my gods?</hi> By which words any man of a reaſonable capaci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty would not otherwiſe apprehend, but
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:119685:58"/> that <hi>Iacob</hi> had done him a great deale of wrong, and he no way faulty. But when he could not prove what he ſaid, then he was faine to condiſcend to the accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation which <hi>Iacob</hi> laid to his charge. Yet becauſe he would ſeeme faultleſſe, he claims propriety in his eſtate of all that hee had, in theſe words: <hi>Theſe daughters are my daughters, theſe ſonne<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> are my ſonnes, and theſe ſheepe are my ſheepe, and all that thou haſt is mine, and what can I not doe this day unto theſe my daughters, or to their ſonnes which they have borne?</hi> Like many Maſters in theſe our dayes, that at their ſervants departure in ſtead of preferring or doing any good for them, charge them with ſuch things they cannot prove: then if they quit themſelves in that, they claim propriety in their eſtate, even as <hi>Laban</hi> in theſe or the like words, All theſe goods are ours, you have got them by us, and now you have got a little, you grow proud, but conſider, that if it had not beene by our meanes, you could never have come to this ſtate, as if they
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:119685:59"/> could divine how God would other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe provide for them, and ſo ſeeme to be very juſt, righteous, and conſciona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble themſelves. The laſt part of <hi>Laban</hi> is his <hi>ſting,</hi> and that hath a poiſonous and venemous quality, and wounds deadly. Which was the envious heart of <hi>Laban</hi> his intents to hurt <hi>Iacob.</hi> But how ſhall I finde them? firſt, in his face by his lookes <hi>Iacob</hi> perceived it well, for ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king to his wives he ſaid, I perceive your fathers countenance is not towards me, as it was wont. Secondly, by his words, his envie appeared in this ſaying, <hi>I am able to doe thee hurt.</hi> As much as if hee ſhould have ſaid, I could finde in my heart to take to my ſelfe all theſe ſheep, and droves of cattell that are mine, and what can I not doe? yea, I am able to doe thee evill, <hi>viz.</hi> to kill thee my in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention is good, <hi>But.</hi> This <hi>But</hi> ſpoiled all: But God forewarned me. Thirdly, his malice appeared by his actions, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides his comming to him, and purſuing him with his brethren, the altering of his wages, and other hard ſervices,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:119685:59"/> which he put him unto; it was very conſpicuous, in requiring of <hi>Iacob</hi> thoſe things which were loſt by caſuality and miſchance, as himſelfe teſtifieth. Whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it were torne by beaſts, or ſtolne by theeves, by night, or by day, he was forced to make it good. Like many ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters in theſe our dayes, that force their poore ſervants to pay for things that are broke, or loſt by caſuality, and their pretence is to make them more carefull, when it is plaine, it is to ſecure their owne goods, and keepe their ſervants the poorer, that they may detaine them the longer in ſubjection. But yet wilful negligence in ſervants ought to bee pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed, elſe they will not care what ſpoil they make of their maſters goods, ſo that by this hard dealing of <hi>Laban, Iacob</hi> told him to his face, that except God had beene with him, hee ſhould have beene ſent away empty, as many ſervants are by ſuch maſters. And thus much I thought good to write, to prove <hi>Laban a Serpent.</hi> And now I ſhould ſhow how this Serpent came to be a ſtaffe of
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:119685:60"/> ſupport to <hi>Iacob.</hi> But before I write any further, I will note the reaſons why <hi>I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaac</hi> ſhould ſend his ſonne, that he had made Lord of his brethren, ſo poorely to ſeeke him a wife: did he forget how his father ſent <hi>Eleazar</hi> of Damaſus, the Steward, and eldeſt ſervant of his houſe in great ſtate, with 10. Camels, richly laden, and ſervants to attend them, to his brother <hi>Nahor</hi> to provide him a wife? or was <hi>Iſaac</hi> now at this time poorer then his father <hi>Abraham?</hi> for anſwer to the firſt queſtion, it could not be that <hi>Iſaac</hi> being a godly man, and ſo brought up from his youth, could for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get a matter of ſuch conſequence. To the ſecond, it's plaine that hee was not poorer then his father, but rather richer. For <hi>Abimeleck</hi> King of the Philiſtins ſaid unto him, <hi>Get thee from us, for thou are mightier then we a great deale.</hi> But the reaſons as I conceive why <hi>Iſaac</hi> ſhould ſend his ſonne <hi>Iacob</hi> away with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any attendance, or other riches, but his ſtaffe onely, as himſelfe teſtifies, was, firſt for ſecrefie, that he might not
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:119685:60"/> be prevented of his journey by his bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Eſau,</hi> who had before vowed his death: for if <hi>Iacob</hi> ſhould have taken any ſervants or treaſure, it would have beene declared to his brother, who, as I ſurmiſe, was Lord of the houſe and ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants, while his father lived. But ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, his father ſent him away thus poorely, to teach <hi>Iacob</hi> that hee ſhould not depend upon his fathers ſubſtance, but upon the bleſſing of God on his owne endeavours, according to theſe words, and <hi>God alſufficient bleſſe thee, and make thee to encreaſe, &amp;c.</hi> Now ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving cleared the way, I will ſhow you <hi>Iacob</hi> walking with his ſtaffe. A man uſeth a ſtaffe for one of theſe ends, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to ſupport him from falling, or elſe to defend him from dangers. An old man uſeth a ſtaffe to ſupport his weake body, and a young man he uſeth a ſtaffe to defend himſelfe, and offend his ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my. In the firſt exception God made this Serpent <hi>Laban</hi> a ſtaffe to <hi>Iacob,</hi> for when he came to <hi>Laban,</hi> he was ſo poor and weake, that he was not of himſelfe
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:119685:61"/> able to ſubſiſt, as by his vow appeares, when he did at that time deſire no more then clothes to weare, and bread to eat: ſo that it ſeemes hee was not very well ſtor'd at that time either with money or proviſion, as he afterwards acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged in theſe words, That he came o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver Jordan with his ſtaffe onely: and in this exigent he was refreſhed and ſupported by <hi>Laban.</hi> Firſt, according to his wiſh, <hi>viz.</hi> with convenient ſuſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance; for I reade nothing to the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary, and therefore judge that <hi>Laban</hi> kept a good houſe for his owne family: ſecondly, with two wives, two maids, twelve ſonnes and one daughter. And laſt of all, with a multitude of riches; ſo that in this he acknowledged Gods great bleſſing towards him, for whereas he came to <hi>Laban</hi> with no more then a ſtaff, now he is become into two bands. But was there not as good ſupporters as <hi>Laban?</hi> could not <hi>Iacob</hi> finde as good maſters as he? yes certainly, for hee might have done as well, if not better, with ſome other. But it was his father
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:119685:61"/> and mothers pleaſure hee ſhould take a wife from among their brethren. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore in obedience to their will he came to ſerve <hi>Laban.</hi> Thus have I briefly declared how <hi>Iacob</hi> was ſupported by a Serpent. But from hence I would have none to inferre, that becauſe he ſerves a <hi>Laban,</hi> therefore he muſt have the bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of <hi>Iacob;</hi> for it was by the provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence of God, and not by <hi>Labans</hi> good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe that <hi>Iacob</hi> became ſo rich: for <hi>La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ban, as a Serpent,</hi> if he had found any of his ſervants idle, or careleſſe, he would be ſure to ſting them. Therefore hee that intends to have the bleſſing of <hi>Ia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cob,</hi> muſt be qualified as hee was, <hi>viz.</hi> Firſt, hee muſt be a pious ſervant, and beginne his ſervice with <hi>Iacobs</hi> wiſh in hearty prayer, that God would bleſſe him therein with food convenient, and clothes to put on, <hi>viz.</hi> ſuch things as are neceſſary for him. Secondly, hee muſt be wiſe to make his bargaine, leſt after much labour, and long time ſpent, he be not ſent away worſe then he came, as the Proverbe is, a young Servingman,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:119685:62"/> and an old begger. For <hi>Iacob</hi> made his bargaine wiſely, for the love of <hi>Rache<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi> he ſerved 14. yeares, and after for the proviſion of his owne houſe hee made ſuch a bargaine, that by policy hee got all <hi>Labans</hi> ſtrong cattell, and left him the feebler.</p>
                  <p>Thirdly, hee muſt bee diligent, as in his owne, ſo in his maſters buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe (but it is fit hee ſhould know what his imployment is) ſo was <hi>Iacob;</hi> for thus he anſwers <hi>Laban, Thou know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt what ſervice I have done thee, and in what taking thy cattell have beene under me (and not under another) thy ewes and thy goats have not caſt their young, and the rams of thy flocke have I not eaten. I was in the day conſumed with heat, and in the night with froſt, and my ſleepe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parted from mine eyes.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Hee did according to the Apoſtles rule, ſerve, not with eye-ſervice of plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing men, but in ſingleneſſe of heart, as unto the Lord, <hi>viz.</hi> he would doe his worke as well behind his maſters backe, as before his f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ce.</p>
                  <pb n="17" facs="tcp:119685:62"/>
                  <p>And laſtly, a good ſervant ought to be wiſe, as to lead an unblameable life, ſo to keepe himſelfe from danger, for in ſuch a ſervice other ſervants, or it may be ſometimes the maſter himſelfe, as here, perceiving that hee thrives or growes rich, preſently grumble or grutch, and ſeeke by ſome wayes or other to defeat him, as here it was: but <hi>Iacob</hi> was wiſe, and could perceive though <hi>Labans</hi> ſonnes uttered that their father thought: for they complained that <hi>Iacob</hi> had taken all that was their fathers, and of his goods he had got all his honours: yet <hi>Iacob</hi> perceived that the countenance of <hi>Laban</hi> himſelfe was not towards him as in times paſt, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he thought it was time to looke a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout him, to avoid ſuch traps and ſnares as might be laid for him: for he knew if he did not prevent them, they would either intangle him in his words, or have ſuch a ſtrict eye over his actions, that one way or other they would find ſome cauſe to quarrell. Therefore at the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement of God, by the counſell
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:119685:63"/> of his wives, he departed with great ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches: ſo that he was able to give his bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther 200. ſhe goats, and 20. he goats, 200. ewes, and 20. rams, 30. milch ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mels, with their colts, 40. kine, and 10. bullockes, 20. ſhe aſſes, and 10. foales, and yet not hurt himſelfe. And thus have I briefly ſhewed how the Serpent was turned to a rod of ſupport, beating away the enemies of <hi>Iacobs</hi> welfare, pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nury, poverty, and miſery: wherein I have diſplayed the prope<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ties of a chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh maſter, and the qualities of a profi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table ſervant.</p>
                  <lg>
                     <l>
                        <hi>But ſuch as</hi> Jacob's <hi>hard to finde,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Though many men have</hi> Labans <hi>mind.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
                  <p>In the conſideration of Gods provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, I am likewiſe to ſhew how God for the reliefe of <hi>David</hi> made wate<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> to flow out of the hard rocke. But in this as in the Serpent, I would not be under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood to meane a naturall, but a meta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phoricall Rocke. And ſuch a Rocke was <hi>Nabal.</hi> And to prove him to bee
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:119685:63"/> ſo, I will not divide him as I did <hi>Laban,</hi> but I will conſider him in the whole, by theſe properties. Firſt by his magni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude; ſecondly, by his obduration; and thirdly, by his ſharpe craggedneſſe. Firſt, a Rocke is a huge bulke of ſtone gathered up to a great height, and <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bal</hi> was exceeding mighty, there's his height; and had 3000. ſheepe, an 1000. goats, there's his bulke. Secondly, a Rocke is a hard ſtony place, ſo that no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing can be got out of it, but by excee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding hard and dangerous labour: and <hi>Nabal,</hi> as his name ſhewes, was of a hard temper, for, <hi>Bray a foole</hi> (ſaith <hi>Salomon) in a mortar, and he will not leave his foo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhneſſe:</hi> hee thinkes himſelfe ſo wiſe that he needs not, or ſo rich and potent that he cares not, or ſo churliſh that hee will not heare any perſwaſions againſt his fooliſh humor. For al the perſwaſive arguments <hi>David</hi> could uſe to draw ſome refreſhment for himſelfe and his men out of this Rock, would not worke upon him, but in ſtead of reliefe, like many in theſe dayes, ſcornes and reviles
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:119685:64"/> at him in theſe words: <hi>Who is David? and who is the ſonne of Iſhai? that I ſhould give my bread, and my water, and my fleſh that I have killed for my ſhearers, and give it unto men whom I know not whence they be.</hi> And yet I am perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded hee was not ignorant that God by <hi>Samuel</hi> had ordained him to bee King<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> over Iſrael, for that was not done in a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> corner, all the Elders of the city of Bethlehem were call<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>d to his anoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting. And <hi>Abigail, Nabals</hi> wife was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fident, <hi>That God would make him a ſure houſe.</hi> But in this <hi>Nabal</hi> was very poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tique, for hee did pretend that <hi>David</hi> was a rebell againſt the Prince, and a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> diſturber of the peace of the Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth, for ſo much his words import, <hi>viz. There be many ſervants that now a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dayes run away from their maſters.</hi> And ſo much for his obduration.</p>
                  <p>Thirdly, a Rocke as it is a hard ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny place, ſo it is a ſteepy, craggy, and dangerous place, either to goe up, or come downe, for man or horſe, if it bee on the land, and in the ſea if a ſhip lights
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:119685:64"/> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>n a Rocke, it is ſurely torne in pieces. Now I cannot tell whether <hi>Nabal</hi> was <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>uch a covetous churle, that ſhips rich<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>y laden, I meane men of great eſtates, were undone by him, in taking the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ent forfeiture of bonds, or other pled<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges; I doe not read that he did ſo grind <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>he face of the poore debitor. Bu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> it is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>laine he was very dangerous fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>gle <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>oore men to come neare: his owne <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ervants could not give him a good word in truth, for in his abſence thus <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>hey ſpake to their miſtreſſe, <hi>Our maſter <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>s of ſuch a curriſh, dogged, wicked diſpoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ion, that no man may ſpeak to him but he <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>leth at them.</hi> And ſo much I thought good to write, to prove <hi>Nabal</hi> a Rocke. And now I am to declare how God made water to flow out of this Rocke: but as I did not deſcribe a naturall rock, ſo I doe not meane naturall water, but metaphoricall, ſomething in the likenes of water; for as water is welcome to a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>hirſty body, ſo is reliefe to the poore; and as water refreſheth the parched ground, ſo doth joy and comfort
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:119685:65"/> the penſive ſpirit. In both which re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpects<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> you ſhall behold water to flow out of this Rocke. Firſt, for the water of reliefe, that's plaine by the Text, for now <hi>David</hi> being purſued by <hi>Saul,</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roſe, and went downe to the wilderneſſe of Pacun, a barren place, where being deſtitute of proviſion for himſelfe and 600. men, ſtrucke this Rocke with the rod of his mouth, in a faire and gentle manner, by friendly and loving ſaluta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, thus: <hi>Both thou and thy houſe, and all that thou haſt, be in peace, wealth, and proſperity. Behold, I have heard that thou <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>aſt ſhearers: Now thy ſhepheards were with us, and we did them no hurt, neither did they miſſe any thing all the while they were in Carmel: aske thy ſervants and they ſhall ſhow thee: wherefore let theſe young men finde favour in thine eyes, for wee come in a good ſeaſon. Give I pray whatſoever commeth to thy hand unto thy ſervants, and to thy ſonne</hi> David. But no water iſſuing forth of this Rock, he did intend to hew it in pieces, as appeares by theſe words: <hi>Indeed I have kept in
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:119685:65"/> vaine all that this fellow had in the wilder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, ſo that nothing was miſſed of all that pertained unto him, for hee hath re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired me evill for good: ſo and more alſo doe God unto the enemies of David, for ſurely I will not leave of all that hee hath by the dawning of the day, any that piſſeth againſt the wall.</hi> And herein <hi>David</hi> was like unto <hi>Moſes,</hi> for God commanded <hi>Moſes</hi> but to ſpeake to the Rocke, and he preſently ſtrikes it. But God pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vented <hi>Davids</hi> ſtriking, for before hee could come to have a view of the rock, the water of reliefe and refreſhment, (200. cakes, and two bottles of wine, 5. ſheepe ready dreſſed, and 5. meaſures of parched corne, 100. frailes of Rei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, and 200. of figs, came purling downe by a ſecret place of the moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine, in a faire and lovely pipe, I meane by the meanes of diſcreet and beautifull <hi>Abigail.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Se<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ndly, for the water of comfort, marke I pray how that flowed from this Rocke. Time was when <hi>David</hi> was had in honour and reputation for
<pb facs="tcp:119685:66" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                     <pb n="24" facs="tcp:119685:67"/> his wiſdome, valour, and skill in mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſicke; ſo that he was praiſed of the wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men in their ſongs<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
                     <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>aul hath ſlaine his thouſand and David h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap> ten thouſand,</hi> loved of all <hi>Iſrael</hi> and <hi>Iuda,</hi> becauſe he went out and in before them, and honoured of <hi>S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ul</hi> himſelfe, though more for feare, then for love, becauſe the Lord was with him, and that he behaved himſelfe more wiſely then any of his ſervants, who promiſed him his eldeſt daughter in mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage to be a ſnare unto him, but deceived him of <hi>Merab,</hi> as <hi>Laban</hi> deceived <hi>Iacob</hi> of <hi>Rachel,</hi> yet when it was told him, that <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chol</hi> his daughter loved <hi>David,</hi> hee was well pleaſed that he ſhould purchaſe her with the hazard of his life, yet where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as <hi>Sa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>l</hi> bargained but for a hundred of the Philiſtins fore-skins, <hi>David</hi> paid him two hundred, ſo juſt are the godly in all their dealings. But he enjoyed the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort of his deare purchaſe but a ſhort time, for then <hi>Sauls</hi> malice began to flame, and plainly to ſhew it ſelfe<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> which a long time before lay hid in the ſtraw of diſſimulati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and hypocriſie, for after that time
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:119685:67"/> 
                     <hi>Saul</hi> hunted after him as a Partridge on the mountaines, as himſelfe complaines, ſo that his ſoule was even parched and dried up with griefe and ſorrow. Now <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> the midſt of theſe troubles, behold how God comforted him, for after hee <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>aw that he was bereaved of <hi>Michol</hi> his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>oving wife, whom <hi>Saul</hi> gave to <hi>Phaltiel;</hi> and after that God had ſlaine his enemy <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>bal,</hi> who ten dayes before his death <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ade a Feaſt like a King. Yet that is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>range, for how could he being a churle <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s the Scripture affirmes, ſpare ſo much <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>oſt, and come into ſuch a merry humor, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s to drinke himſelfe drunke? Me thinkes <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e ſhould bee rather tearmed a generous Gentleman, a good fellow, and a joviall Companion. Oh me! I have found it he as a churle for all that, for he made a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ſt like <hi>Dives,</hi> to the rich and mighty, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ch as himſelfe, and was merry with <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>em, to keepe himſelfe in good reputati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> with great men of the world, but had <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> care of poore <hi>Lazarus</hi> that was ready ſtarve at his gate for want of cloathes cover his naked, diſeaſed body, and
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:119685:68"/> bread and drinke to ſatisfie his hungr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> and thirſty appetite, he did not rememb<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> the afflictions of <hi>Ioſeph,</hi> nor the troubles <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>David,</hi> and for his ſervants he could o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>der them well enough, ſo that as he live ſnarling, and barking like a dogge, ſo he dyed grumbling and grunting like a hog and for ought I know without any repen<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tance of his former evill life, becauſe it ſaid his heart dyed within him, and be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>came like a ſtone, which was more f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> feare of the danger he was in, then for an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> remorſe he had of his ſinnes: yet out <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> this ſtony hard rocke God brought th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> water of comfort to <hi>David</hi> in a loving beautifull and religious wife, whoſe nam<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>Abigail</hi> ſignifies the fathers joy, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> ſhe became the joy, ſolace, and comfo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> of <hi>Davids</hi> ſoule, an helper in all ex<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gents by wiſe and godly counſell, for <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>vid</hi> had experence of her great godllin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> wiſdome, and humility: And what gre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter comfort is there in this world the ſuch a woman? Surely none. All the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> things by a learned penne might be fu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ther enlarged, amplified, and illuſtrated
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:119685:68"/> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ut it is enough for me by this, to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>der Gods providence towards his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>hoſen.</p>
                  <p>Therefore I will conclude, and pray <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> God, that it would pleaſe him to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>ſe into my heart the graces of his holy <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>pirit to bee ſo qualified as <hi>Iacob</hi> and <hi>David, viz.</hi> fervent in prayer, and hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>le in heart, ſorrowfull for my ſinnes <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s <hi>David,</hi> righteous in my actions as <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>acob,</hi> loving to my enemies as <hi>David,</hi> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>evalent with God as <hi>Iacob;</hi> ſo ſhall not need to feare the churleſſeneſſe of <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>abal,</hi> or malice of <hi>Laban,</hi> which is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> one being both churles, for read <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>aban</hi> backwards its <hi>Nabal</hi> forwards, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>or the power of <hi>Eſau,</hi> or envy of <hi>Saul,</hi> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nd what need I to care, though <hi>Shemei</hi> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ile, or <hi>Labans</hi> children murmure, for have hereby learned that God can, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>d will for the ſupport, reliefe and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>omfort of his children, make poyſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ous things wholeſome, and bitter <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ings ſweet, turne Serpents into rods, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>d rockes and hard ſtony places into a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ft and gentle temper, as it is in the
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:119685:69"/> 107. <hi>Pſal. He maketh the wilderneſſe a ſtanding water, and water ſprings of a dry g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ound &amp;c.</hi> to the end of that Pſalme. And ſo much I thought good to write o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> the providence of God towards his choſen.</p>
                  <p>The ſecond part of this Diſcourſe is like a paire of Ballances, for in the one ſcale, you may behold the love of <hi>Iſaac</hi> towards <hi>Eſau,</hi> and in the other you <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>y ſee the love of <hi>Iacob</hi> towards <hi>Io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeph.</hi> In the firſt, I will ſet the pride of the world, and in the other, I ſhall fix the humility of the godly; ſo that the light vanity of the one, and the true va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lidity of the other may eaſily be diſcer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned. But this theame is more harde<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> then the rocke I laſt handled, and hee had need of more then a ſerpentine wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, that ſhall undertake to unfold the knotty windings in ſuch a Labyrinth. Yet becauſe God hath bleſſed me with two children, I will write ſomething in my youth which I ought to performe if it ſhall pleaſe God to bleſſe me with old age. Therefore in <hi>Iſaacks</hi> love to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="29" facs="tcp:119685:69"/> 
                     <hi>Eſau,</hi> I will note three things. Firſt, what <hi>Eſau</hi> was, and how <hi>Iſaac</hi> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rought him up. Secondly, what <hi>Eſau</hi> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>id, and how his father approved his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ctions; and thirdly, I will briefly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare how <hi>Eſau</hi> was prevented of that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e ſought for, and how his father re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tarded him. For the firſt, which was <hi>Eſaus</hi> minority, it cannot be thought o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>herwiſe, but that <hi>Iſaac</hi> according to his Fathers example, did bring up his chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren in the feare of the Lord, and eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially him, that he thought to make Lord of his brethren, for this is the Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimony of God concerning <hi>Abraham, I know him, that he will command his houſhold after him, that they keep the way <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>f the Lord, to do righteouſneſſe and judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, that the Lord may bring upon Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham that he hath ſpoken unto him.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Therefore I beleeve that <hi>Iſaac</hi> did of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>en tell <hi>Eſau</hi> and the reſt of his family <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>hat God had done: how he had crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted the world of nothing, how hee up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holds and guides the frame thereof by his providence: how the Angels for
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:119685:70"/> their pride and ambition were throwne downe into hell: how <hi>Adam</hi> brough<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> ſinne upon himſelfe and all his poſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity: how God had promiſed to reſtore<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> falne man to his former happineſſe by Chriſt, the ſeed of the woman: how his fathers lived in hope of that promiſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> a godly, righteous and ſober life. And how God bleſſed them with temporall bleſſings, and ſpirituall graces, for their faith and obedience. But all thoſe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructions would not take effect in <hi>Eſau.</hi> His very name ſignifies, that he ſough<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> more after earthly fading happineſſe then for ſpirituall and heavenly graces for <hi>Edom</hi> ſignifies a piece of red earth and <hi>Eſau</hi> working; and as his name is, even ſo is he: for notwithſtanding all the godly precepts and religious practices of his father, whoſe cuſtome was to goe out into the fields to pray and meditate on the wondrous workes of God. <hi>Eſau Edom</hi> was ſtill working in the earth, giving his minde to ſenſua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity and pleaſure, for ſo much his deſire after Lentill potage, and cunning hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:119685:70"/> import: yet it may be he as many others of his conditions made a ſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blance and ſhow before his father of godly and pious qualities, being endued with much knowledge, and could talke prettily to his father thereof, and it may be gained the love of his father before his brother in this reſpect, as well as for his activity and skill in hunting in his youth: ſo that his father doted too much upon him, for this hath beene the quality of many godly parents in all ages, to humor their children too much in their youth, which they perceiving, know very well how to plot and bring to paſſe their deſignes: for by nature mankinde is more apt and prone for the obtaining of earthly fading tranſitory treaſure, then for heavenly, durable, and everlaſting felicity. But this natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall promptitude is very hard and diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cult to diſcerne: <hi>Iſaac</hi> could not deſcry it in <hi>Eſau,</hi> and therefore I ceaſe to won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der that aged people who are farre infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riour to <hi>Iſaac</hi> in ſpirituall ſpeculation, cannot diſcerne it in this age. Therefore
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:119685:71"/> leaving the education of <hi>Eſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>u,</hi> I come <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>o his youth, the ac<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ions of <hi>Eſau's</hi> life, the Text ſaith <hi>He became a cunning hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tter, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                           <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi> Now I reade in ſacred W<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> before him, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> after him: therefore I ſurmiſe that he as <hi>N<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>mrod, the mighty hunter before the Lord,</hi> ſought more af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter worldly honour and glory then ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſtiall treaſure, for they are alike in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny things. Firſt in their names, <hi>N<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>mrod</hi> ſignifies <hi>Rebellious,</hi> to note his pride, cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elty, and rebellious courſes, in erecting a <hi>Babel,</hi> whoſe top might reach unto heaven: for many authors affirme, that he out of his pride and ambition ſpake to the people theſe words, <hi>Come let us build us a City and a Tower whoſe top may reach unto heaven, that wee may get us a name, leſt wee bee ſcattered upon the whole earth,</hi> and ſo compelled the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple to hard labour, leſt they being idle, ſhould reject the tyrannicall juriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction which was ſo great, that God confounded his enterpriſe, and ſo in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſufferable, that all men abhorred his
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:119685:71"/> inſolency, ſo that it came into a Proverb, when people ſaw proud tyrants to beare rule, to ſay <hi>He was as Nimrod the mighty hunter before the Lord;</hi> agreeable hereun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to is the ſurname of <hi>Eſau, Edom,</hi> which ſignifies bloudy or red, to note his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vengefull and bloudy minde, for after he had a long time hunted beaſts, he began to hunt after the lives of men, as appeares by his threatning to kill <hi>Iacob,</hi> and by his fathers words at the denouncing of his bleſſing, <hi>By thy ſword ſhalt thou live.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>But as <hi>Nimrod,</hi> ſo <hi>Eſau,</hi> for all his plot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting and threatning was confounded in his enterprize, for he was his brothers ſervant in poſterity. Againe, <hi>Nimrod</hi> was a great and mighty King, and his Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritories of a large extent, even from Babel to the end of the earth for ought I know, becauſe it is not ſpecified; and <hi>Eſau</hi> was a mighty man, the Captaine of foure hundred men, a great company in thoſe dayes, and from him ſprang many Dukes and Kings, the firſt that I read of Dukes in ſacred writ, as appeares in his Genea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logy, ſo it is very conſpicuous, that <hi>Eſau</hi>
                     <pb n="34" facs="tcp:119685:72"/> bent all his minde for the obtaining worldly honour and applauſe, yet note it further in the ſtory, rather then he would want good cheare to fulfill his wanton appetite, he would ſell his birthright, like many flouriſhing gallants in our dayes, that rather then they will leave their laſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vious courſes in gaming, revelling, and ſwaggering, will make ſale of all that their parents and friends left them; for what cared <hi>Eſau</hi> for his fathers bleſſing, ſo hee might fare well, and goe bravely, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the faſhion of the Countrey. Here I might touch the vanity of phantaſticke apparrell in theſe dayes, but I know it is a thing indifferent, and thererefore paſſe it over, and come to conſider how <hi>Iſaac</hi> liked all this, alas good man! he could not perceive it, the love of veniſon had blinded his eyes. Now I would gladly know what veniſon it was that <hi>Iſaac</hi> lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved. I read that <hi>Rebeccas</hi> ſavory meat was two Kids, and for ought I know <hi>Eſau</hi> launted for a Bucke or a Doe, a Stag or a Hinde, but becauſe it is not expreſſed in a metaphoricall expoſition, I ſurmiſe it
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:119685:72"/> was his flattering, inſinuating and collo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guing diſpoſition, for ſurely <hi>Iſaac</hi> could not chuſe but ſee that <hi>Eſau</hi> was worldly minded, both by his habit and behaviour; but eſpecially in the choice of his wife, whoſe Idolatrous and rebellious courſes were a griefe of minde to him, and <hi>Rebec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ca,</hi> ſo that ſhe complained, that ſhee was weary of her life for the daughters of <hi>Heth,</hi> yet <hi>Iſaac</hi> for the love of Veniſon (ſo powerfull is naturall affection in the heart of mankinde) called to give him the bleſſing of the elder brother, and forgot <hi>Iacob</hi> who had before purchaſed that Birthright, of which I beleeve his father was not ignorant, like many rich men in theſe dayes, that as the Proverb is, love to have their elbows clawed, and delight to thinke their poſterity ſhall flouriſh in the world after their deceaſe, care not what they give to maintaine pride and prodiga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity, but take little or no care at all for the poore and deſtitute. In the laſt place, I am to ſhew how <hi>Eſau</hi> was prevented in that he intended, and how <hi>Iſaac</hi> rewarded him for his Veniſon: for the firſt, while
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:119685:73"/> 
                     <hi>Eſau</hi> was hunting to get ſavoury meat, ſuch as his father loved; <hi>Rebecca</hi> that knew her husbands appetite, as well as <hi>Eſau,</hi> and could blinde his judgement, as well as his ſight, daintily cheated him, becauſe ſhe loved <hi>Iacob,</hi> in whom ſhe ſaw the graces of Gods Spirit ſhined bright, and did beleeve, that hee was the Sonne of Promiſe, according as God told her at his birth, <hi>That the elder ſhould ſerve the younger;</hi> and as ſhe perceived by his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious and godly exerciſes in the courſe of his life, therefore ſhe prepared ſavoury meat, ſuch as ſhe knew her husband lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, and compelled <hi>Iacob</hi> her younger ſonne, to preſent it to his father in the name of his brother, who very feare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full of a curſe, rather then a bleſſing, did performe her will; for hee knew ſuch cunning plotting, and indirect meanes by hypocriſie, and diſſimulation to accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſh their deſignes, was both hatefull to men, and abhomin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ble in the ſight of God, yet I note it, to ſhew the ſubtilty of a woman to obtaine her deſires, for it is very likely that ſhee perſwaded <hi>Iſaac</hi>
                     <pb n="37" facs="tcp:119685:73"/> that <hi>Iacob</hi> was her elder ſonne though his voice declared the contrary.</p>
                  <p>But p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſſing by that alſo, I am in the laſt place to demonſtrate what was the reward that <hi>Eſau</hi> received for his great labour in hunting. It's plaine he did deſire with <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laam</hi> to have the bleſſing that <hi>Iacob</hi> ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>planted him in, and ſought it with teares.</p>
                  <p>But ſeeing be could not obtaine that, he deſired one bleſſing of his father: and ſo according to his requeſt enjoyed the fat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of the earth, and dew of heaven from above, <hi>viz.</hi> he lived in a fertile and fruit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full countrey, hee did not want for any earthly bleſſing, and was a man of great power and authority, for from his ſtocke came many famous Kings, as is before expreſſed, ſo that as he hunted for world<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly honour, he did enjoy it.</p>
                  <p>Now to make a concluſion of the whole matter, I ſhould ſhow the love of <hi>Iacob</hi> toward <hi>Ioſeph,</hi> the firſt borne of <hi>Rachel</hi> his firſt love. But what ſhould bee the reaſon that <hi>Iacob</hi> fixed his love more on him then all his breth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ren?
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:119685:74"/> Was it becauſe he brought to their father their evill ſayings? No ſurely, for <hi>Iacob</hi> as a godly man did not delight to heare any ſlanderous reports, for he knew that tale-bearers and buſie bodies in other folkes matters, doe ſet houſes and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monwealths in diviſions. The Text ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders the reaſon thus, becauſe he begot him in his old age, and that might very well be, for experience ſhowes, old folke love little children more then young doe, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe there is a ſympathizing affection be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene them, as the proverbe is, An old man is twice a child. But the reaſon as I conceive, why <hi>Iacob</hi> loved <hi>Ioſeph</hi> more then all his brethren, was, becauſe he ſaw in him a promptitude to the ſervice of God, and divine ſpeculation, more then in his brethren, and that he was of a harm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe, innocent, and ſweet diſpoſition, ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peares plainly; for though hee knew his brethren hated him, becauſe of their fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers love towards him; yet hee loved them, and would bee telling them his dreames, for which they hated him ſo much the more, which in my
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:119685:74"/> opinion was very improvidently done; for we ought to avoid, and not to run headlong into danger, and this raſh con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſing with his enemies, almoſt coſt him his life: firſt, by putting him into a pit, and then ſelling him to perpetuall ſlavery. Yet this is, and was ever for the moſt part the practice of the moſt zealous godly, to ſpeake or doe ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing at which the worldly wiſe taking advantage of, bring them into great perſecution and trouble, as it was here. But what care they for ſuch affliction, if God ſee it good for them? And what cared <hi>Ioſeph</hi> for his brethrens ſpleene, ſo <hi>his father noted his ſayings.</hi> Now if from hence I could learne according to <hi>Salomons</hi> rule, to traine and bring up my children in the feare of the Lord in their youth, that ſo they might not for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get it when they be old: to bend the twig while it is young, leſt when it is growne to a tree, it be paſt my ſtrength to bow or governe, as <hi>Eſau</hi> was for <hi>Ia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cob, Hophni</hi> and <hi>Phinehas</hi> for <hi>Eli,</hi> &amp;c. then I ſhould thinke my ſelfe a happy
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:119685:75"/> man. And this is the principall reaſon why I ſpend all this labour in looking after a diſcreet and vertuous woman, to helpe mee as well in the education of theſe two Infants I have, as thoſe that it ſhall pleaſe the Lord to ſend me by her, that ſo having for the duration of my ſervice lived as <hi>Iacob,</hi> I may likewiſe as hee become into two bands.</p>
                  <p>Thus have I given vent to this new wine, and becauſe it is new, ſome flying lees may be found therein: but if it bee well ſetled upon a ſound judgement, the lees will ſinke to the bottome, and being clearly rackt, the pure liquor may bee exerciſed for many profitable uſes. The pure liquor, if there be any found therein, I doe humbly acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge is Gods worke, but the filthy lees and unwholſome dregs is mine. Let God have the praiſe of the good, but let me have the blame and ſhame of what is ill done: ſo ſhall the glory and praiſe of God be the <hi>Alpha</hi> and <hi>Omega</hi> of all my workes. Therefore Oh! that
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:119685:75"/> God would worke in me both the will and the deed, of his owne good plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, that it would pleaſe him to gr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nt the deſires of my heart, and requeſt of my lips, that all mens thoughts, words, and actions, and mine eſpecially, may redound to the praiſe and glory of God, and not for any vaine applauſe before men, to the good and welfare of Gods choſen, and not for any by-reſpects, and to the joy and comfort of our owne ſoules in the day of the appearing of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt in glory, when hee ſhall render to every one according to the workes hee hath done in this life: that every conſcionable Saint may then heare that joyfull welcome of his Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our and Judge, <hi>Well done good and faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full ſervant, enter into thy Maſters joy<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                     </hi> Which bleſſed happineſſe God in mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy grant to mee, and all his choſen, not for any merit of our owne, which is nothing but damnation of ſoule and body for the beſt good that ever we have done o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> can doe. But for the alſufficiency and meritorious ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferings
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:119685:76"/> of Chriſt Jeſus in our nature here upon earth. To whom, with his all-glorious Father, and ſoule-ſanctify<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Spirit, three Perſons, and yet but one true eſſentiall God, be aſcribed by me, and all creatures, as is moſt due, all honour, glory, praiſe, thankſgiving, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doration, and obedience, from this time forth, and for evermore.</p>
                  <closer>Amen.</closer>
                  <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:119685:76"/>
                  <p>A STARRE. OR, Briefe and pleaſant Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations of Love.</p>
                  <q>
                     <bibl>Judg. 5. 20.</bibl> 
                     <hi>The ſtarres in their courſes fought againſt Siſera.</hi>
                  </q>
                  <p>
                     <figure>
                        <figDesc>printer's device of William Ley or Lee, featuring a star</figDesc>
                        <head>
                           <q>Stella effulget in noctu</q>
                        </head>
                     </figure>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="proem_poem">
                  <pb facs="tcp:119685:77"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:119685:77"/>
                  <head>The Proem.</head>
                  <head type="sub">Primo Die Januarii, 1640.</head>
                  <lg>
                     <l>
                        <hi>GReat</hi> Julius Caeſar, <hi>did ordain,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Compoſe, and frame the</hi> Julian <hi>yeare,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>And was the firſt that gave the name</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>
                           <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nto this day, as may appeare;</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>And cald it</hi> New-yeares day, <hi>thereby to ſhow</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>How we in <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>irtue ſhould begin to grow.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Now of all Vertue</hi> Love's <hi>the Queen,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Which is compriſed in this Booke,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>And in her Liverie I am ſeen,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Wherefore do not diſdain to looke</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Into this ſame, which is</hi> a New-yeares Gift</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>From a kind friend whoſe love doth ſeldom ſhift,</hi>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
                  <closer>
                     <salute>Vale</salute>
                  </closer>
               </div>
               <div type="invocation_poem">
                  <pb facs="tcp:119685:78"/>
                  <head>Invocation.</head>
                  <lg>
                     <l>
                        <hi>O Holy glorious, ever loving God,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Who art the fountain, and the living ſpring</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Of Godly Love; diſtill it all abroad</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Into my Soule, that I from thence may bring,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Such liquor good, that I therewith may cheare</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>My Godly friends that are to me moſt deare.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>
                        <hi>O thou that art the Sun of holy Love,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Inflame my heart, by thy bright beames of light,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>That I may ſole delight in things above;</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Let this ſame holy fire burn day, and night</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Within my Soule; that ſtubble, chaff, and hay</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Of hate, and envie may ſoone waſt away.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>
                        <hi>But what am I, that dare ſo boldly write</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>
                           <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pon ſo holy and divine a thing?</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>I have no judgement or wit to indite,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>O thou canſt water out of hard Rocke bring.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Pardon my error, guide me by thy ſprite,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Direct my judgement, in that I ſhall write, Amen.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div type="poem">
                  <pb n="1" facs="tcp:119685:78"/>
                  <head>A STARRE. A briefe Meditation of Gods Love in generall, and in ſpeciall to me.</head>
                  <lg>
                     <l>
                        <hi>OH what a taske have I here ta<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ne in hand?</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Vnder whoſe waight</hi> Atlas <hi>could hardly ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d;</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>No ſtout</hi> Alcides, <hi>or great</hi> Sampſon <hi>ſtrong</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Were able to ſuſtain this burden long:</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Then What am I, that I ſhould dare to write</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Of the great Lo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>e o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> God, that's infinite?</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>I might as well, number the Oceans ſand,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Count the graſſe piles, that grow upon the land;</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Give the true ſum of all the ſpangled ſtarrs,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Or truly ſhow the totall of our haires;</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Nay, I could ſooner empty th'Ocean dry</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>With a ſmall ſpoone, then tell this miſtery</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Of Gods great Love to man, how ſhould I then</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>With unlearn'd wit, and an untutr'd Pen,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Dare to ſet forth, ev'n in the leaſt degree</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>His Love to all, but moſt of all to me?</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>And yet, becauſe God in his word hath ſhowne</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>His Love to man; and therein made it knowne</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>It is his will, that we ſhould make relation</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Of all his favours to the generation</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>That ſhall ſucced us, I will truly ſhew</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>What I of Love out of Gods word do know.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <pb n="2" facs="tcp:119685:79"/>
                     <l>
                        <hi>And yet I cannot tell how to begin,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>In ſuch a Sea of Love I'm plunged in:</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>For whether I looke on the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>arth below,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Or up to heaven God doth his great Love ſhow,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>In three great ſtreams me thinks his Love doth run</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>
                           <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pon mankind, in t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>mporall bleſſings ſome,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Th'others Spirituall Grace, the third is Glory,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Oh where, or how ſhall I begin this ſtorie?</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>For, if I ſhould of earthly bleſſings ſpeake,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>My Brain's too ſhallow, and my wit's too weake;</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>But much more unfit to relate a ſtory</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Of ſpirituall Graces, or eternall Glory;</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Yet what unto my mind God hath me ſhowne</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>I hope he will aſſiſt me to make knowne:</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>And, firſt of all there comes into my mind</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>The wonderfull creation of mankind;</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>And here, the Love of God did great appears</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Before mankinde was made a houſe to reare,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Like to a loving Friend unto his Gueſt,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>He would prepare his houſe and ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>e it dr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ſt,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>And all things very neate for his delight,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>All this to welcome an unworthy wight;</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>For God made earth mans footeſtoole, heav'nly light</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>As a faire Canopie both day and night:</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>But when he was to make mans noble features,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>He did not ſay as unto other Creatures,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Be made, <hi>and</hi> it was ſo; <hi>but he did call</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>A Councell with himſelf, and then he all</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Mans body made, and did his breath infuſe.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <pb n="3" facs="tcp:119685:79"/>
                     <l>
                        <hi>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>t upon what things ſpeaks my unlearn'd Muſe?</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>y that deſire more of this thing to know,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>armed</hi> Du-Bartas <hi>will divinely ſhow:</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> is enough that my unlearned Pen</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> this can ſhew Gods kindneſſe unto men,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>d unto me, for he hath well endu'de</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>y mind with knowledge, his ſimilitude</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ſtampt in me, my bodi's right and ſtraight,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>d every part (though little) hath its waight;</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>nd this, by Gods great Love I do enjoy</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>un many are perplext with much annoy.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>e next great bleſſing that from Gods Love flowes</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> preſervation, as in years man growes,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>om many perills, and great dangers ſtrange,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ich in the univerſe by courſe do range:</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> be preſerv'd from the diſaſtrous ſtormes</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> weathers tempeſt, which do bring great harmes</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>on mankind, and from the wrackfull water,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>m fiery flames, and from the banefull ſlaughter</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>umane Creatures make, freed from Warre,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>m hungry famine, and Plagues deadly skarre,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>e tokens ſure of Gods meere Grace and Love,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> which ſometimes he doth his Children prove:</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>t Gods great preſervation is not all</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>s Love to Man in bleſſings temporall.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> he hath on them providentiall care</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>t onely to keepe ſafe, but to prepare</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>uch earthly comforts in this preſent life,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>d the chiefe of them is a Godly wife;</hi>
                     </l>
                     <pb n="4" facs="tcp:119685:80"/>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Becauſe that ſhe the minde doth helpe and eaſe,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>But health and wealth the body onely pleaſe,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Yet health and wealth, honour and liberty,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Are the rare gifts of Gods benignity:</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>So are good friends a comfortable ſtay</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>
                           <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nto a poore man, in an honeſt way.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>And all theſe favours God hath given me,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>For which I never can too thankefull be.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>For firſt, when I was naked, weake, and poore,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>And by my Parents turned out of doore:</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>There did the Lord of me take care and charge,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>And out of miſery did me inlarge</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>And brought me in a comfortable place,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Where I did firſt begin to long for Grace.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Yet there, three yeares I followed vaine play,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>But at the laſt I did breake off that way</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>And went about a new worke to upreare,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>But in the ſame I was ſcant halfe a yeare;</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>And I no ſooner came to know the parts</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Of Latin Language, the true grounds of Arts</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>For me the Lord a Maſter did provide,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>With whom this ſixteen yeare I did abide,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Yet many times I did occaſion ſind</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>To ſearch and trie what was hid in his mind;</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>But when by all the meanes I could deviſe,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>I could not bring to paſſe mine enterpriſe,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Yet ſtill imploide to rub, to ſcrape, and ſweepe,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>And ſo for ſix yeares ſpace he did me keepe;</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>I gave him juſt offence; and fled away</hi>
                     </l>
                     <pb n="5" facs="tcp:119685:80"/>
                     <l>
                        <hi>But there it was not Gods will I ſhould ſtay.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Then after nine yeares with him was ſpent out,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>I did begin again, to looke about</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>For ſome proviſion, of which I had hope</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>For to obtaine, whereto I bent my ſcope,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>And ſo by prayer, intreaty, and perſwaſion</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>God did even bend, and bow Wills inclination</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>(By Aexholmes accident, and french affaires,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>By bodies grievance, and ſome other cares)</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Yo doe ſome good, for me, and my kind mate,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Whom God hath taken from this mortall ſtate:</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Here did appeare the wondrous worke of God;</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>In turning of the Serpent to a Rod:</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Now had I braines, or wit I could well ſhew</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>How God made water from the Rock to flow:</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>For humbly I confeſſe by his kind favour,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>And Gods bleſſing on my poore endeavour,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>I got proviſion for my loving mate,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>My ſelfe, and children in contented ſtate,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>And ſtill enjoy the bleſſings of this life</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>As health, and wealth, I only want a wife,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Of whom I hope I ſhould much comfort find</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>To eaſe and give reliefe my troubled mind;</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>But I am like a Mole hid in hard earth,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>If once go<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> in, I hardly can get forth:</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Therefore to God with winged prayer I'leſly,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>That he would raiſe my minde to things on high<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                        </hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Oh Lord do thou infuſe into my mind</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Such ſacred wit, that I thy Love may find</hi>
                     </l>
                     <pb n="6" facs="tcp:119685:81"/>
                     <l>
                        <hi>That's ſpirituall, but this is Infinite;</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Ther's no man able to deſcry that light,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Then how ſhall I, that am an unlearn'd wight?</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Yet what learn'd men from Gods word hath reve<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>
                        </hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>I may as well declare as keepe conceild,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Eſpecially if't be to make a ſtory.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Of Gods eternall Mercy, Love, and Glory,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Therefore ſeeing that my unlearned quill</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Hath thus begun, it ſhall continue ſtill</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>This Love to ſhew, by the aſſiſting might</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Of God, who out of darkneſſe can bring light.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>And firſt of all there's great manifeſtation</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Of Gods great Love, in mans predeſtination;</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>That he ſhould</hi> Eſau <hi>hate, and</hi> Jacob <hi>Love,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>It only came of mercy from above,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>But 'gainſt</hi> Charybdis <hi>and</hi> Caphorian <hi>Rock,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>My ſhallow veſſell I meane not to knock:</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>But longſt the ſhore with ſailes of faith I'le coaſt</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>My Starre the Bible, Steer-man the holy Ghoſt</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>For I too bold, will not aske how or why</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>God hath ordained thus mans deſtiny:</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>For me, It's enough, to know that my eſtate</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Is firme in Chriſt, elſe I am reprobate.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>But ſecondly, in our ſacred vocation,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Of Gods great love, ther's clearer demonſtration;</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>For was it not great Love, in God, to chuſe</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>From other Nations the unthankefull Jewes?</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>To give them Laws, Statutes, and Sacraments</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Of future Bleſſings, and to ſhew the events</hi>
                     </l>
                     <pb n="7" facs="tcp:119685:81"/>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Of the</hi> Meſſias, <hi>by Prophets inſpiration?</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>But 'tis a greater happineſſe unto our Nation,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>That we are free from the whores wofull wrack,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>That unto errour we have turn'd our back,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>That God hath brought us into wondrous light,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>That of his Goſpell we have the cleare ſight,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>That we ſuck nouriſhment from ſacred Writ,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>That we enjoy ſuch ſpeciall benefit</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>As are the Sacraments, and word of God</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>In peace, and joy free from th' afflicting Ro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>
                        </hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Of Gods juſt wrath; but whither do I goe</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>have much more of Gods great Love to ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                              <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                           </gap>,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>In the Redemption of ſinfull mankind,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>But how, or which way ſhall I bend my mind<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                        </hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>The wondrous Love of God, therein, to ſhow</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>How to beginne, or end, I doe not know.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Waſt not great Love that God became a man,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>That that Infinite ſhould be within a ſpan,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>That Deity, ſhould become fleſh and bone,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>This cannot by a mortall man be ſhowne,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>et it is true, God did deſcend from high</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>And tooke on him ſinfull mans miſery.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>His Birth was rare, his life was mean and poore,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>And in his body all mans ſins he bore:</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>But oh! what greater Love can there be ſhowne</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Then for a friends life to lay downe his owne:</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                              <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                           </gap> this did Chriſt, ſinfull mans debt to pay<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                        </hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>His Fathers wrath, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                              <desc>•••</desc>
                           </gap>ry <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>o allay?</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>And by his death, he did full well expell<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                        </hi>
                     </l>
                     <pb n="8" facs="tcp:119685:82"/>
                     <l>
                        <hi>The power of ſinne, and the dread pains of hell;</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>If I could write of all the wondrous Asts</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Of Chriſt our Saviour, and his noble facts,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>I then ſhould want both Paper, Pen, and Inke</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>To utter that which my poore heart doth thinke:</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>I am not able fully to relate</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>The rare example of his earthly ſtate:</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Oh! how ſhall I then into heaven fly,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>There to behold this lorious myſterie?</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>How that he roſe from death I cannot ſhew,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>But how he did aſcend, I faine would know,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>For I was borne upon Aſcention day,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Therefore to follow him I dayly pray;</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>But ther's ſuch Plumets ty'd unto my h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ele</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>That drawes me backward, that I cannot feele</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>His Godly motions, yet his love I finde</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Deepely ingraved in my ſinfull mind:</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>I did intend to write of faith in Chriſt,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>How thereby juſtifi'd, how that did conſiſt</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>In free forgiveneſſe of our former crimes</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>To live more Godly, in the after times:</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Then, did I purpoſe for to make relation,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>How for to know our free juſtification,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Not by mans workes, but by the holy Ghoſt</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Inſpiring ſaving faith; but</hi> I <hi>almoſt</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>In this moſt ſacred Theme, my ſelfe had loſt;</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Then how wee're juſtifi'de, therein to ſhew</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>What Graces in Repentance Garden grow:</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>How in the heart ſprings ſorrowfull Contrition;</hi>
                     </l>
                     <pb n="9" facs="tcp:119685:82"/>
                     <l>
                        <hi>How in the lips doth ſprout humble Confeſſion,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>How ſatisfaction from the hands d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> flow</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>To them we wrong'd, Rep<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                              <desc>•••</desc>
                           </gap>ance true to ſhow</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>How wee ſhould die to ſinne, and live to God,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>But in this Theam I make too long abode.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Yet not too long, but that my Wit's unable,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>My Brain's too ſhallow, and my ſelfe unſtable;</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Therefore i'll leave it unto all Divines,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>That in ſuch things ſhould ſpend their pains and times:</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>For <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> have ſmall skill in me to reveale</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>The Love of God which I muſt needs conceile,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>For that bright glory, I cannot expreſſe;</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>It is encit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>h, that my we<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ke ſhallowneſſe</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Can on<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ly thinke of that ſame mighty power</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Which is prepared in that heavenly Bower;</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>For to deſcribe it, fully, any man</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>By pen and inke neuer be able can,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Therefore <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                              <desc>••</desc>
                           </gap>e draw a v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>il<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> before mine eyes,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Not d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ring to behold ſuch myſteri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>s</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Which is ſo great, th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> like never eye ſaw</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>This well is deepe, I have no pale to draw;</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Eare h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                              <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                           </gap>h not hard, nor the heart underſtood</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>What God prepara'hath, for his childrens good,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>How, as his earthly Globe doth f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>r ſurpaſſe</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>In beauty and a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>lights that darkeſome place</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Of our Nativity, ſo, heav'nly bliſs</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Doth farre <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>urmount all that in this world is.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>How mortall bodies ſubjest to corruption,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Shalbe immortall without interruption:</hi>
                     </l>
                     <pb n="8" facs="tcp:119685:83"/>
                     <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                        <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="9" facs="tcp:119685:83"/>
                     <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                        <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="10" facs="tcp:119685:84"/>
                     <l>
                        <hi>How that the ſoule ſhalbe fil'd with the ſight</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Of God, and Saints, in that Celeſtiall light;</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>And there I hope for to behold my wife,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>For here ſhe liv'd a Godly quiet life.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Oh<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> here is Love paſt all mans apprehenſion,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>And therfore farre beyond my dull invention.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Therfore I'll ceaſe in this diſcourſe and pray,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>That God may keepe me in a vertuous way;</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>That I in God may comprehended be,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>For I'm not able to hold him in me.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Yet why thus ſay I, if I living be,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>I truely dwell in God, and he in me:</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>For God is Love, and he that dwels in Love</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Doth dwell in God; but this is farre above</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>My apprehenſion, fully to relate,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>The rare conjunction of this hapy ſtate.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Oh<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Lord I pray thee, ſend thy Love in me</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>That I againe may returne mine to thee,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Then ſhall I praiſe thee, with a thankefull heart,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>When thou thy Love, thus to me doth impart:</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Now I'll conclude with praiſe unto thy might,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>For thus inabling my weake hand to write.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
                  <closer>Soli Deo Honor &amp; Gloria</closer>
               </div>
               <div type="tract">
                  <pb n="11" facs="tcp:119685:84"/>
                  <head>A briefe Meditation of Mans Love.</head>
                  <p>LOve is a Paſſion of the heart ſeated in the affections, and called by the Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſophers <hi>A menta<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap> vertue;</hi> becauſe it is a longing deſire of the minde to be uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to the beloved object. There are three kindes or ſpecies of Love. The firſt is divine, ſpirituall, and heavenly. The ſecond is carnall, earthly, and ſinfull. The third is humane, civill, and naturall. The firſt love is pious, and onely makes hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py. The ſecond is ſinfull, and only makes miſerable. The third is vertuous, and commendable. The firſt love, is proper to the pious Religious man. The ſecond, is proper to the ſinfull wicked man. The third, is proper to the civill honeſt man.</p>
                  <p>Thus Love may be compared to water conveied from the fountaine of the heart
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:119685:85"/> in theſe three pipes; firſt, if we conſider this liquor running in the firſt channell, then we ſhall finde it to bee pure, cleare, and the onely ſaving water of life: In whoſe heart ſoever this divine, ſpirituall and heavenly liquor ſprings, ſhall never thirſt, but reſts alwayes ſatisfied; in pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ty <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>mper<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>te and humble, and in adverſity he is patient and meeke; in what ſtate of life ſoever hee is in, hee is therewith content: He is in this world, but is not of this world: He uſeth the things of this life, as though he uſed them not; his delight is in grace and goodneſſe, and all evill wayes he utterly abhorres; for although he walketh upon the earth, his converſation is in heaven; he is truly a heavenly minded man, he really fulfilleth the commandements of the firſt Table in the Decalogue, he loves the Lord with all his heart, with all his minde, and with all his ſtrength; nothing is ſo comfortable to him as the favour of God, nothing ſo fear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full as his diſpleaſure, nothing ſo deſirable as grace, and nothing ſo ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>efull as ſinne, while the ſhip of his ſoule doth ſayle upon
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:119685:85"/> the troubleſome waves of this miſerable world: no ſtorme of perſecution can ſtay or hinder his heavenly courſe of godli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, till it arive at the haven of eternall happineſſe: becauſe the anchor of this ſhip is a ſtedfaſt hope caſt upon the firme rock Chriſt Jeſus; her cables are a ſtrong con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidence faſt bound to the maine maſt of a lively, ſaving and juſtifying faith, her la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding is no vaine merchandize or trumpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, but rare jewells, and coſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>y orna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, even the rich treaſury of the gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of Gods Spirit. The Pilot is the word of God which at the laſt will guide her to the deſired haven. This man wa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>kes upon the earth as a ſtranger and pilgrim. The world is but his Inne, wherein hee lodging for a night, departeth in the mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning; Heaven is his Countrey, there reſts his love, there lyes his treaſure, there is his heart; here he hath many enemies, the luſt of the fleſh, luſt of the eyes, and pride of life. The world, the fleſh and the Divell, againſt theſe he is ſtrongly ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med with the whole armour of God, for the defence of the head, the helmet of
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:119685:86"/> ſalvation, for the defence of the heart; the breſtplate of righteouſneſſe for the loines, the girdle of verity; for the ſafe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guard of the feet, ſhoos of the preparation of the Goſpell of peace, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>or the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence of the whole man, the ſhield of faith, wherewith he quencheth all the fiery darts of Satans ſuggeſtions, blunteth the edge of the worlds allurements, and dulleth the heat of fleſhly temptations; his offenſive weapon is onely the ſword of the Spirit, which he cunningly uſing cutteth off all ſinne, for the word of God is lively, and mighty in operation, ſhar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per then any two edged ſword, for it cut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth through even to the dividing aſſunder of the ſoule, and the ſpirit, and of the joynts<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and the marrow: It is an axe with which the whole tree of ſinne, with his forbidden fruit is hewn downe with theſe weapons, the man that is inflamed with the love of God, will trample upon the fleſh, deſpiſe and contemne the world, reſiſt the Divell; and at the day of death by the aſſiſting grace of his Captaine Chriſt Jeſus, will conquer and overcome
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:119685:86"/> ſinne, death and hell, and be carried by the Angells of God into heaven, the place of happineſſe, where he ſhall hold a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petuall feaſt, ſing an everlaſting ſong, weare an incorruptible Crowne, poſſeſſe an eternall Inheritance, and fully enjoy his love, with endleſſe joy, content and reſt.</p>
                  <p>Secondly, if wee conſider this liquor running in the ſecond current, then wee ſhall finde it to bee muddy, foule, loath<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome, and the onely poyſonous and ſoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>killing water, in whoſe heart ſoever this carnall, earthly, and ſinfull liquor ſprings, ſhall ever thirſt, and never be ſatisfied: he is in every thing contrary to the former lover, hee is never contented with his e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate: In proſperity he is proud, preſump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous, and cruell; and in adverſity hee is deſperate, fretfull, and envious. His minde is onely upon earth, and fading tranſitory riches: hee careth for no heavenly grace, ſo he may have carnall pleaſure: he takes no care for his ſoule, but all his care is to pamper his body: he accounteth the god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſimple fooles, and eſteemes them as the
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:119685:87"/> off-ſcowring among the people: he boaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth himſelfe in the multitude of his riches, and ſolaceth himſelfe in his pleaſures: he thinkes hee ſhall live for ever upon e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>th, and puts the day of death a farr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> off: hee ca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>eth not by what meanes he getteth <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>is riches, ſo hee may goe bravely, and fare deliciouſly every day. Thus the lover of carnall and fl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſhly delights will not feare to commit adultery, gluttony, drunken<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, &amp;c. fulfill the d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſire or luſt of the fleſh. And thus the l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ver of the world will venture to comm<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>t cove<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ouſneſſe, op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion, cruelty, &amp;c. to fulfill and ſatisfie the luſt of the eyes, and pride of li<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e. The man th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>t is inflamed with this love, liveth upo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>he earth as a Citizen in his owne C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 words">
                        <desc>〈◊◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> the world dand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 words">
                        <desc>〈◊◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> child<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>ding his deſire with rich<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 words">
                        <desc>〈◊◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>: <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> fl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſh p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>mpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>h him as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 words">
                        <desc>〈◊◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>eding his deſire with pl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ſure and d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>; and the Devill foſtereth him as his father, by perſwading him that he is in a happy condition, yet he is in ſubjection to the world, a ſervant to the fleſh, and a ſlave to the divell. Thus
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:119685:87"/> he lives in ſeeming happineſſe, and dyes in reall miſery, and or one drop of the ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow of comfort, loſeth an Ocean of true conſolation.</p>
                  <p>Thirdly and laſtly, if wee looke upon this liquor running in the third pipe, wee ſhall finde it to be clean good, and whole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome wa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>er. I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> whoſe heart ſoever this humane <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>vi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>l, and naturall liquor ſprings, may reſt ſatisfied for a time, but this can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not give the heart any true content, except it proceed from the firſt love, which in a good Chriſtian are never ſeparate: for he that truly loveth God, will love his bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther alſo; but he that hath not this chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table love, for ſo we may terme it, cannot have the firſt love, as the Apoſtle teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fieth, ſaying, <hi>If any man ſaith hee loveth God and hateth his brother, he is a lyar; for how can he that loveth not his brother whom he hath ſeene, love God whom hee hath not ſeene?</hi> Yet this love may be without the firſt, as appeares in divers of the Heathen Philoſophers, who have exceeded many Chriſtians in morall vertues, yet were without the divine, ſpirituall, and heaven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:119685:88"/> love, for they did not know God, nor the myſtery of godlineſſe: and therefore had no faith, and conſequently could not have the firſt love, which proceedeth from faith. The man that is inflamed with this love, doth really fulfill the command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of the ſecond Table in the morall Law; he loves his neighbour as himſelfe, this is a true charitable man; he hath diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſed abroad and given to the poore, hee doth much good in the world, he relieves the needy, helpes the oppreſſed, feeds the hungry, inſtructs the ignorant, comforts the comfortleſſe, &amp;c. he layes for him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe here a good foundation by good workes, and ſhall at the laſt receive the reward of his labour, if he faint not. This love doth in large it ſelfe into three ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall ſpecies or pipes. In the firſt runnes that humane love wherewith we love all mankinde, as they are men of one com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon nature with us. In the ſecond runnes that civill love wherewith wee love our owne Countrey and Nation, as they are men brought up under one civill govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in Lawes and Religion with us: and
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:119685:88"/> in the third pipe runnes that naturall love wherewith we love our kindred or friends as they are of the bloud, or to whom wee are bound by ſome ſpeciall obligation of amity. To let the humane and civill love runne out as men are pleaſed to convey it forth from the fountaine of their heart, I will onely fix my meditations upon this naturall love, and of that I will not write any thing of the love of parents to their children, or brother to brother, &amp;c. al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though I know their love may bee very great. But I will onely inſiſt to write what that natural love is wherewith a man is af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected to a woman. And herein I would not bee underſtood to meane that luſtfull love which is commonly covered under this title, although experience ſhewes that it is very powerfull in whoſe heart ſoever it is kindled, and is a raging paſſion, as all love is, if it bee not kept in, as fire within the chimny, &amp; the ſea within his bounds: It is a fooliſh madneſſe, a labyrinth of er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour, and a miſerable thraldome before it can be obtained. But if the lover doth ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fill his deſire, what hath he got but a racke
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:119685:89"/> to his minde, a torture to his ſoule, a gib<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bet to his conſcience, a ſtaine to his repu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, and a pleaſing, yet fatall poyſon. This breeds a conſumption in his purſe, rottenneſſe in his bones, and a blot in his good name. But if this love bee in the lawfull way of marriage, as this kinde is ſeldome to that effect, then if the lover doth make his choice onely for the beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of the body, without any reſpect to the qualities of the minde, hee may finde one that may pleaſe his eye, but commonly ſhe proves a wanton <hi>Hellen</hi> or a trayterous <hi>Dallila,</hi> one that will conſume his wealth, and worke his deſtruction: or elſe ſuch a one that will make him a ſcoffing ſtocke to the world, by cunning planting upon his head <hi>Acteons</hi> livery. Thus for plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure he gets miſery, and for a beautifull outſide embraceth a ſnake in his boſome, poyſon in his meat, and gall in his drinke. Againe, I would not bee underſtood to meane that covetous deſire which is alſo commonly clothed with this title, and in theſe dayes chiefly embraced, when a man doth onely chuſe a wife for riches, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:119685:89"/> hee cannot like her perſon, much leſſe love her. Such may meet with one that may fulfill his deſire with wealth, but commonly ſhe proves a ſcolding <hi>Xantippe,</hi> one that will be alwayes ſcolding, railing, and taunting him, and with whom hee ſhall never live one quiet houre. Thus for a little wealth he is alwayes pinched with a ſtrait ſhooe, lives in continuall vexation, and at the laſt is forced to leave her, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he cannot live quietly with her. But this is not the love which I purpoſe to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribe, for this is carnall, earthly, and ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, but the other is naturall, honeſt, and commendable, which is an honeſt deſire of the minde to bee joyned to a woman, not ſo much for her outward perfections, as for her inward vertues; not onely for her wealth, but for the love of her perſon, ſo it goes equally betweene theſe two, and exceeds in neither, for it is grounded upon the true cauſes for which matrimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny was ordained, <hi>viz.</hi> for the prevention of ſinne, for the mutuall ſociety, comfort, aide, aſſiſtance, counſell, and advice of a
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:119685:90"/> diſcreet, vertuous, and loving companion, in all exigents; and to bee carefull in the bringing up or education of their children in the feare of God, that they prove not curſes rather then bleſſings. I did conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der all the kindes of love in the metaphor of water, I will now turne the phraſe, and write of this in the metaphor of fire. In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed the pious love which was the firſt, and the charitable love which was the laſt, may very well be compared unto wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, which is of a heavie nature, for it runs very ſlowly in the hearts of the children of men, and cannot be drawne out of the fountaine of the heart without great force, and ſtrong pumping: the reaſon is becauſe it doth not ſpring there, for it is infuſed by the Spirit of God. But<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> the other love, which is carnall, earthly, and ſinfull, doth flow from thence in great abundance, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it naturally ſprings there, and may better be compared to fire, which is of a light nature, for wickedneſſe burneth as a fire, which will conſume both body and ſoule, if it be not prevented by repentance.
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:119685:90"/> So alſo this naturall love burneth as a fire in an honeſt heart, which is infuſed by a divine power, and not by our owne cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt reaſon or judgement. Now as fire I will conſider it in 4. things: in its ſmoke, or manifeſtation; in its fire, or augmenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; in its flame, or confirmation; and in its aſhes, or conſummation. Firſt, conſider this fire of true love in its ſmoke: it is a common proverb, <hi>Where there is ſmoke there is fire;</hi> ſo where there are apparent manifeſtations of love, there is love. The ſignes of love are theſe, in the tongue, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lightfull ſpeeches; in the eyes, amorous lookes; in the countenance, modeſt baſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſſe; in the hands, liberall preſents; and in the face, active nimbleneſſe to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine the beloved object. But if this love goes no further, then it is eaſily quenched with a drop of the water of rejection, or trod out with the foot of diſdaine.</p>
                  <p>But in the ſecond place, if fuell bee ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to this fire, <hi>viz.</hi> if there be a mutuall and ſympathizing affection betweene the lover and his love, then it burnes mighti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:119685:91"/> and ſhowes it ſel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e to be true love; then the lover with his love ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>h but one heart, though two bodies. The lover is even moulded into the ſubſtance of his love. If it come to this height, no water of ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſity can quench it, or winde o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> peoples tongues blow it out: the feare of pove<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ty, the perſwaſions of friends, the allurements of riches, or the in<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ements of pleaſures, cannot move, much leſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e rem<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ve it. There is no way to extingu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſh this fi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e, but to take away the fuell, and then it dies: But the place will be ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ene where it hath been, the heart will grieve, the eye weepe, &amp;c. to thinke how fooliſhly paſſionate he hath beene, and for the time to come, the lover will learne to be more wary in his choice.</p>
                  <p>But in the third place, if this fire con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinues ſtill burning, that it comes to flame, if it continue to be confi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>med, either by a reall contract before God and their owne conſcience, which is commendable: for we read that <hi>Ioſeph</hi> and <hi>Mary</hi> were thus contracted before they were married. And it is grounded upon this reaſon, to breed
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:119685:91"/> in them a longing deſire <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>o enjoy the fru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ition of their hopes; or by publique ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remony of the Church before men, for there is little difference betweene theſe, in effect they are all one. But it is very fit every thing amongſt Chriſtians ſhould be done in decent order, and not like bruit beaſts, or the heathen that know not God: then there is no putting of it out, not al the fa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>re pretences in the world can ſalve ſuch a breach, and they themſelves ſhall finde it to be a clog to their conſcience, a burden to their eares, and a web in their eyes, to thinke of, heare, or ſee the beloved party. To violate faith and troth in this kinde e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecially, is a thing odious in the ſight of God, abominable in the ſight of men, and a moſt intolerable vexation to themſelves. Oh! let all honeſt people take heed leſt they make ſhipwracke of faith and a good conſcience.</p>
                  <p>Fourthly and laſtly<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> if this flaming fire goes not out, but continues in its bright luſtre, till the fuell bee quite conſumed, <hi>viz.</hi> till death depart: the aſhes that is
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:119685:92"/> left behinde is the rare example of vertu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous love and mutuall ſociety: like that of the Turtle with his mate.</p>
                  <p>Thus have I briefly declared the pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of mans love, I pray God grant I may embrace the beſt, and caſt the worſt from me, ſo I ſhall be truly happy.</p>
                  <closer>Amen.</closer>
                  <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
                  <pb facs="tcp:119685:92"/>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
      </group>
   </text>
</TEI>
